<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An inquiry into the remarkable instances of history and Parliament records used by the author of The unreasonableness of a new separation on account of the oaths, whether they are faithfully cited and applied.</title>
            <author>Brady, Robert, 1627?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7290</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12325430</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12325430</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29174)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 204:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An inquiry into the remarkable instances of history and Parliament records used by the author of The unreasonableness of a new separation on account of the oaths, whether they are faithfully cited and applied.</title>
                  <author>Brady, Robert, 1627?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A criticism of Edward Stillingfleet's 'A discourse concerning the unreasonablness of a new separation'"--BM.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Written by R. Brady. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Discourse concerning the unreasonableness of a new separation.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59535:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN INQUIRY Into the Remarkable Inſtances of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> and <hi>Parliament Records,</hi> uſed by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of a new Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration on Account of the Oaths;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are faithfully cited and applied.</head>
            <p>THE Author of this Diſcourſe makes Enquiry into two things, to clear what he hath before delivered.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 12.</note>1ſt. <hi>How far the Diſcharge or Releaſe from a Perſon, who hath Right, and is concerned, is neceſſary to thoſe who take the Oaths of Allegiance to another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Poſſeſſion of the Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, <hi>How far</hi> our Saviour's <hi>Rule holds in this Caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Theological</hi> part of this Diſcourſe I wholly pretermit, and leave it to <hi>Divines;</hi> the Hiſtorical is only that I ſhall enquire into.</p>
            <p>And before I enter upon this Enquiry I ſhall Note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the <hi>Saxons</hi> were a miſcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laneous People, joyned with the <hi>Francks</hi> in Piracy and Rapine; who made De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcents wherever they could upon the Coaſts of <hi>Gallia, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Britain,</hi> as <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> lib. 27. c. 7. and l. 28 c. 7. <hi>Bede</hi> in his Hiſtory fol 58. col. 2. adds the <hi>Jutes</hi> and <hi>Angles</hi> to thoſe, who came or were invited into <hi>England.</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> adds to theſe the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Friſons,</hi> in his <hi>Chronology</hi> at the end of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> and moſt certainly under the names of <hi>Saxons</hi> were comprehended ſeveral other People; ſuch as joyned with them in Rapine and Piracy, or ſuch as they had ſubdued, which by the Conquering <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> or Neighbour Nations, had been forced for their own ſafety into Iſlands, Bogs and Moraſſes, upon and near the Coaſts of the <hi>German</hi> Sea, from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Eydor</hi> in <hi>Juteland</hi> to the <hi>Elve,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Scheld;</hi> and it may not want probability, that the <hi>Heptarchy</hi> was here erected by the Leaders of ſeven different ſorts of People, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Pillagers under the names of <hi>Saxons.</hi> Such as they were when they came, they remain'd, eſpecially during the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> always Invading, Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and Burning one anothers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, frequently killing and murthering their Kings, Earls, or Chief Governours, or thoſe one another. So, as I think, very Judicious Men would not look for Authentick and Well-grounded Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the Hiſtory of theſe times; where things were always in a Flux, without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59535:2"/> permanent ſettlement, or amongſt the barbarous Uſages of theſe rude, illiterate People; unleſs in ſuch Caſes as may have a great appearance of Truth, and are reported or confirmed by the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent of their Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>The order of Succeſſion was certain in the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Kingdom, after <hi>Egbert</hi> brought the greateſt part of the <hi>Heptar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> under his Power and Government. Yet from the various Expreſſions of the ancient Writers of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Story con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Succeſſion, an unwary Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would think that the <hi>Saxons</hi> agreed not in one Rule of Succeſſion, or that they had no Rule at all; but whoever conſiders with underſtanding, what thoſe Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſay, will find they purſued a <hi>ſure Rule of Succeſſion</hi> (as much, and as often as thoſe times would permit) which was either Right and Proximity of Blood; or the Nomination and Appointment of a Succeſſor by the Precedent King; which Nomination by the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, before the <hi>Danes</hi> came in, moſtly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Minority or Nonage of their Children, and that only in the turbulent State of the Nation, <hi>in turbulento Reipub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licae tempore,</hi> which was thought and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a ſufficient Cauſe, for the Father to prefer his Brothers Son before his own,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vit. Ael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred.</hi> fol. 9. ſect. 10. lin. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or a Baſtard before his lawful Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, <hi>ut pater fratris filium proprio, vel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Nothum anteferret Germano.</hi> And by the following Inſtances it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, That the <hi>Saxons</hi> did in their own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Subjection and Submiſſion to their Princes, acknowledge both Proximity of Blood, and Nomination by their Kings often both together, ſometimes only one of them, but never followed any other Rule, nor did the People in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarchy ſet up any King themſelves in any formal, or pretended Aſſembly of the Nation. Of both Titles in the ſame Perſon, there are theſe three Examples before the <hi>Danes</hi> Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Egbert</hi> the firſt <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarch had two Sons, <hi>Ethelwolth</hi> and <hi>Aethelſtan;</hi> the Eldeſt ſucceeded him in the Kingdom of the <hi>Weſt Saxons;</hi> and he gave to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Son <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> what he had ſubdued, or his Conqueſts; who died obſcurely, it not being known what end he came to.<note place="margin">Malmsb. de Geſt. Reg. Ang. f. <hi>20.</hi> a. <hi>n. 30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ethelwolphus Weſt-Saxonum regno contentus, caetera quae pater ſubjugaverat, Appendicia, Aethelſtano filio contradidit, Qui quanto &amp; quo fine defecerit incertum</hi> The <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology Ann. Dom. 836. hath it thus. <hi>Ethelwolphus Occidentalium Saxonum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num capeſſit, (<hi>Feng to Weg-Sexana Rice,</hi>
               </hi> the Common expreſſion for Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that Language) <hi>filio autem ſuo Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtano, Cantuariorum, Saxonum Orientalium, Suthregientium, &amp; Suth Saxonum regnum donavit. Florence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in the ſame year thus. <hi>Cujus poſt mortem</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Egbert) Ethelulphus filius ſuus in Weſt-Saxonia regnare coepit, ſuumque filium Aethelſtanum Cantuariis, East-Saxonibus, Suth-Regiis, &amp; Suth-Saxonibus regem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecit. Egbert</hi> made his Son <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> King of <hi>Eſſex, Kent, Surrey,</hi> and <hi>Suſſex.</hi> After whoſe death the whole Kingdom came into the hands of <hi>Aethelwulph.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Teſtam. Aelfred.</hi> in <hi>Aſſer. Meneven.</hi> f 22. n. 20. <hi>Malm.</hi> f. 22. <hi>a.</hi> n. 20. <hi>b.</hi> n. 30. chron. <hi>Saxon. Anno</hi> 854.</note> 
               <hi>Aethelwulph</hi> notwithſtanding his Sons by Proximity of Blood were his Heirs, and alſo Heirs to one another; yet gave his Kingdom of the <hi>Weſt Saxons</hi> to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelbald</hi> his Eldeſt Son, <hi>Ethelred</hi> his third, <hi>Aelfred</hi> his fourth Son ſucceſſively; and gave to his ſecond Son <hi>Ethelbert, Eſſex, Kent, Surry, Suſſex. Ethelhald</hi> lived but five years, and <hi>Aethelbert</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the whole Kingdom as next Brother, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t juſtum erat,</hi> ſays <hi>Aſſer.</hi> f. 4. n. 40. <hi>Flor. Worceſt.</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Anno. 860.<note n="†" place="margin">Chon. Saxon. Anno. <hi>860.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aethelbaldus autem Quinquennium regnabat <hi>(Feng Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryht, to Eallum Tham Rice his Brother)</hi> Ethelbertus autem totum fratris ſui regnum capeſſit.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Flor. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Anno. <hi>866, 871.</hi>
               </note> After whom his two younger Brothers <hi>Aethel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed,</hi> and <hi>Aelfred</hi> were poſſeſſed of the Kingdom ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This Hiſtorian calls this Teſtament or Will <hi>Epiſtola haereditaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Id. Anno. <hi>975.</hi>
               </note>So King <hi>Edward</hi> poſſeſſed the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom after his Father King <hi>Edgar,</hi> both by Proximity of Blood, as his Eldeſt Son; and by his Fathers Donation, and Command, <hi>&amp; Edwardum, ut pater ejus praeceperat, eligerunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Flor. Wig. Anno.</hi> 975.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59535:2"/>
            <p>From <hi>Egbert</hi> the Firſt <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarch, to <hi>Ethelred</hi> the laſt <hi>Saxon</hi> King, by Prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imity and right of Blood, for the ſpace of 216 years, we do not often find the words Elected, or Election; and where they do occur, they are bound and limited by Proximity of Blood, or Nomination of the Succeſſor by the Predeceſſor: and as they are uſed, they ſignifie only <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition of,</hi> or <hi>Submiſſion to</hi> him, that was ſaid to be Elected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Danes</hi> (a promiſcuous People as the <hi>Saxons</hi> were, <hi>Danes, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegians, Goths, Sweves, Friſons,</hi> &amp;c. and under the name of <hi>Danes</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aelfred vit.</hi> f. 10. c. 14.</note>) ever ſince the beginning of King <hi>Egbert,</hi> having by continued Invaſions, and Piracies, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed, and grievouſly waſted and moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>England,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Ael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,</hi> by pact and bargain between him and <hi>Guthran,</hi> enjoy'd <hi>Eaſt Saxony,</hi> or <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> and the County of the <hi>Eaſt Angles;</hi> and, as<note n="*" place="margin">Faedus Aelfr. &amp; Guthr. <hi>c. 1.</hi> Lamb. <hi>fol 36.</hi>
               </note> ſome ſay, a far greater part of the Nation. In King <hi>Ethelred</hi>'s Reign, <hi>Swane,</hi> King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> with a great Army Invaded, and made himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the whole Nation; forcing <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> and his Wife <hi>Emme,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> with their two Sons <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Alfred</hi> into that Country.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings ſtayed not long here after <hi>Swane</hi> had conquer'd the Kingdom; they all four Reigned not much above 25 years, their only Title was the Sword; notwithſtanding they either brought hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cuſtom of the Predeceſſors naming, or giving the Kingdom to his Succeſſor, as probably it might have been ſome times practis'd in their own Kingdoms; or uſed it as they found it here practis'd in caſes of Neceſſity, and in their Childrens Minority by the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Emmae pr.</hi> by <hi>du Cheſn</hi> amongſt the old <hi>French</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. fol. 164. B.</note>
               <hi>Swane</hi> made his Son <hi>Cnute</hi> his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. He married <hi>Emme</hi> the Widow of <hi>Ethelred,</hi> by whom he had his Son <hi>Harde Cnute.</hi> To him his half Brother <hi>Cnute</hi> gave all that had been any ways under his Government; but he being then in <hi>Denmark,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> C.</note> 
               <hi>Harold</hi> poſſeſſed himſelf of the Kingdom; who was a Baſtard Son of a Maid Servant brought into his Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines Chamber, and impoſed upon him by her;<note place="margin">Fol. 174. A. B.</note> and for this reaſon <hi>Elnoth</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> refuſed to Conſecrate him King, and to deliver him the Crown and Scepter.</p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Harold, Harde Cnute</hi> called his half Brother <hi>Edward</hi> by his Mother <hi>Emme</hi> (afterward called the Confeſſor) out of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and cauſed him to live with him; and dying within leſs than two years after, left him Heir of his whole Kingdom,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gul. Geme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticens.</hi> l. 6. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Totius regni re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquit haeredem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he, not long before he died, made <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror</hi> his Succeſſor. <hi>Anno eodem</hi> (viz. 1065.<note place="margin">Note the Reaſon.</note>) <hi>Rex Edwardus ſenio gravatus cernens Clitonis Edwardi nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per defuncti filium Edgarum, Regio folio minus idoneum, tam corde, quam corpore, Godwini<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Comitis multam malam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Quotidie ſuper terram creſcere ad Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum ſuum Wilhelmum Comitem Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae animum appoſuit, &amp; eum ſibi ſuccedere in regnum Angliae voce flabili ſancivit.</hi> In the ſame year King <hi>Edward</hi> growing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm with Age, perceiving <hi>Edgar Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the Son of Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> lately Deceaſed, neither in Mind nor Body fit for the Government, nor to bear up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the growing Power and Malice of <hi>Godwin</hi>'s Sons, thought upon his Couſin <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Normandy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 511. b. n. 30.</note> and by a firm Declaration Decreed he ſhould be his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor in the Kingdom. <hi>Ingulph</hi> that Reports this, was at the very time Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taty to this <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and after he had given him a great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter for his Courage, Conduct, and conſtant ſucceſs in War; his Juſtice, Religion, and Devotion, ſubjoyns, that King <hi>Edward</hi> ſent <hi>Robert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as Envoy to him, to let him know he was deſigned his Succeſſor in his Kingdom. Which probably he would never have done, if this and the like Donations had been queſtion'd in thoſe days. Nay<note n="†" place="margin">Review of Tyrhs, p. 482.</note> Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> ſays, <hi>This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was a lawful Title.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:59535:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>William Rufus</hi> had the ſame Right and Title of Succeſſion by the Donation of his Father, and as his Teſtamentary Heir<note n="*" place="margin">Fragmt. de vitâ Gul. long. f. <hi>32.</hi> n. <hi>20. 30. 40.</hi> Orde. Vit. f. <hi>39.</hi> C. D.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ralph de Diceto,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, (who lived in or very near the time) ſays,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 505. <hi>n.</hi> 40. 50.</note> That <hi>Hugh Bigod,</hi> Steward of the King, made ſpeed out of <hi>Normandy,</hi> (where King <hi>Henry</hi> died) into <hi>England,</hi> and made Oath before the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> That upon his Death bed, upon ſome Differences that hapned between him and his Daughter the Empreſs did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherit her, and made <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Boloign</hi> his Heir. Whereupon <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> giving too much credit to the Words of the Steward, conſecrated <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Mortaign</hi> King at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> If this ſhould be true, he ſucceeded as Teſtamentary Heir to King <hi>Henry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>John</hi> was Teſtamentary Heir to his Brother <hi>Richard;</hi> who upon his Death-bed, when he deſpaired of Life, deviſed to his Brother <hi>John</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and all other his Lands, and made all preſent ſwear Fealty to him, and commanded that his Caſtles, and Three parts of his Treaſure ſhould be delivered to him.<note n="*" place="margin">f. <hi>449.</hi> b. lin. <hi>37.</hi> Walſ. Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podig. Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriae f. <hi>457.</hi> n. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Roger Hoveden,</hi> who was a Domeſtick in the Family of King <hi>Henry</hi> II. and wrote at this very time, delivers this.</p>
            <p>King <hi>John,</hi> before he left the World, made <hi>Henry</hi> his Firſt-begotten Son his Heir. <hi>Paris,</hi> who<note n="*" place="margin">f. <hi>288.</hi> lin. <hi>2.</hi> Mat. Weſt. f. <hi>276.</hi> n. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> writes this, was Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian to this <hi>Henry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After what hath been premiſed, the Author's Hiſtory comes to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered upon his firſt Query, which he maintains upon Inſtances in the <hi>Saxon, Norman,</hi> and ſubſequent times.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>P.</hi> 13.</head>
               <q>As to the former, I ſay, the reſolution of Conſcience in this caſe doth not depend upon the Will and Pleaſure of the Perſon to whom the former Oath was made, but upon the ground on which it was made, and from which it had its force to oblige; and if thoſe ceaſe, the obligation of the Oath ceaſes together with them: And whether they do or not, no particular Perſon is ſo fit to judge, as the Three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Realm, as I ſhall now prove from ſeveral remarkable Inſtances to this purpoſe in <hi>our Hiſtories</hi> and Parliament Records; <hi>whereby I ſhall make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</hi> that when a Diſpute hath hapned about the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and to whom the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> were to be made, they have looked on it as their proper Right to limit the Succeſſion, and determine the Oaths.</q>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Author's Words, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication continued <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 13.</head>
                  <q>V;nder the <hi>Britiſh Government,</hi> we find a conſiderable Inſtance to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Vortigern,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A.G. <hi>454.</hi> Magnates Brit. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Vorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gernum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimiter fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſuum in Regem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limaverunt Mat. Weſt. <hi>p. 83.</hi>
                     </note> the Britiſh King had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into <hi>a Secret League</hi> to bring over the <hi>Saxons:</hi> upon which the <hi>Great Men of the Nation deſerted him, and choſe</hi> Vortimer <hi>in his room</hi> (he was his eldeſt Son.) Here it is plain, they thought the introducing a Foreign Power, a ſufficient diſcharge of their Obligation to him, it being ſo directly contrary to the <hi>publick Good</hi> of the Nation, although <hi>Vortigern</hi> gave them no Diſcharge.</q>
                  <p>In the Deſertion of <hi>Vortigern</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing his Son <hi>Vortimer,</hi> he cites <hi>Mat. Weſt. Anno Domini</hi> 454. But in the whole Story there is not one Syllable of a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret League</hi> in <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi> in that, or in any other following Year. What he cites in the Margin is in <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>To prevent the Eaſineſs, Supinity, Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury and Effeminacy of all People; the Ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norance, Avarice, Debauchery, and Simony of the Clergy; and an univerſal lapſe of the Nobility and People into notorious Extravagancies and Impieties; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the Violences, and hinder the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions and Invaſions of the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots; Vortigern</hi> held a Counſel of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59535:3"/> Great Men and Nobles, being excited thereto by the Noiſe and Clamours of the People; wherein, by <hi>General conſent,</hi> it was <hi>agreed</hi> to call the <hi>Saxons</hi> out of <hi>Germany</hi> to their aid. Who no ſooner received the Invitations from the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> by ſpecial Meſſengers, but eaſily granted, what they themſelves had a Thouſand<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gildas.</hi> pag. 46, 47, 48, 49.</note> times wiſhed for. <hi>Vortigern</hi> excited by the noyſineſs of his People about the Publick State, <hi>asked the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of his Great Men; and it pleaſed <hi>them all</hi> to call the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> out of <hi>Germany,</hi> Mighty in Arms, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, without Habitations, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a double Profit, that they might eaſily conquer their Enemies; and that hitherto, being void of Habitations, they might eſteem it a vaſt benefit to inhabit a naſty Soil, or Poor Country: But they were not to attempt any thing againſt the <hi>Britains,</hi> becauſe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the Advantage they received by coming thither, would ſoften, and reduce their natural Ferity or Barbarity. The Advice was allowed, and there were ſent into <hi>Germany</hi> Envoys, very conſiderable Men, and ſuch as worthily repreſented the Nation. The <hi>Germans</hi> hearing what they had a Thouſand times wiſhed for<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Malms.</hi> fol. 3. b. <hi>n.</hi> 10.20.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they enter'd at firſt with great Joy<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> n. 40. 50.</note> and Favour of the People: but finding they cheated them, and came for their Eſtates, when it was too late they would have<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> f. 4. <hi>a.</hi> n. 20.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd them. They leagued with the <hi>Scots,</hi> whom they were ſent for to expel, pretending they were not ſufficiently rewarded, and provided for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with their Aſſiſtance waſted, burnt, and ſpoiled all Cities and Countries from the Eaſt to the Weſt Sea<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gild</hi> c. 24. p. 55, 56.</note>.</p>
                  <p>Part of the Story cited by this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, tho he mentions only <hi>Mat Weſt.</hi> is from <hi>Geofry</hi> of<note n="*" place="margin">Fol. 48. <hi>b.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Monmouth,</hi> the moſt Fabulous Hiſtorian (if he be worthy to be called ſo) extant amongſt the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and therefore, it may be ſuppoſed, this Tale is brought in by a ſide Wind, and father'd upon <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lues acerrima, &amp; acrior mox hoſtium novorum,</hi> i. e. <hi>Anglorum eſt ſequuta,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Flor. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn. <hi>f. 541.</hi> Ann. Dom. <hi>446.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Quos Britanni unanimi conſilio cum Rege ſuo Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerio, quaſi Defenſores Patriae, ad ſe invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandos eligerunt, ſed ſtatim Impugnatores &amp; Expugnatores ſenſerunt.</hi> A more ſharp, than the ſharpeſt of Plagues followed, which was of the new Enemies, the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whom the <hi>Britains,</hi> by Unanimous Counſel and Advice with their King <hi>Vorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gern,</hi> had choſen to be invited to them, as <hi>Defenders of the Country,</hi> but they preſently proved Aſſaulters of it, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors. The <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Anno.</hi> 446, 447</note> And the late <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s agrees with, and approves of theſe Relations of the <hi>Britains</hi> joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their King <hi>Vortigern,</hi> in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the <hi>Saxons,</hi> in his learned Book <hi>of the Antiquities of the Britiſh Churches.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 304. 317, 318</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">In the Saxon times <hi>Sigebert</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons</hi> (in the time of the <hi>Heptarchy</hi>) was complain'd of for <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government,</hi> and <hi>for changing their Laws</hi> for his own ends: but when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in his way, there was a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nobility and People (<hi>conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerunt Nobiles regni cum populo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi>) and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared themſelves free from Allegiance to him, and choſe <hi>Kineulfus</hi> in his room<note n="*" place="margin">Cum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem modi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> omnibus male tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaret eos legeſque a teceſſorum ſuorum propter co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modum ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um vel d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pravaret, vel muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Mat. Weſt. A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>756.</hi> He Hunt. <hi>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> p. 196.</hi>
                     </note>.</q> The following words here omitted in both Authors are, <hi>Kineulfus. Juvenis egregius de Regiâ ſtirpe oriundus, electus eſt in Regem.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>Both <hi>Hen.</hi> of <hi>Hunt,</hi> and from him <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi> have this Story. But 'tis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe reported, and by <hi>Florence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Fol. 57 <hi>An. Dom</hi> 755.</note>. <hi>Kineulfus de Proſapiâ Regis Cerdicii oriundus; auxilium ſibi ferentibus Weſt-Saxonicis Primatibus, Regem illorum Sigebertum ob multitudinem ſuorum facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum iniquorum regno exterminavit, &amp; loco ejus regnavit. Kineulphus</hi> of the Stock of <hi>Cerdic,</hi> (who was the firſt <hi>Saxon</hi> King)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59535:4"/> by the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, for the multitude of his wicked Actions (that was <hi>Kineulf</hi>'s pretence, and without doubt a <hi>Common Good</hi> tacked to it) expell'd <hi>Sigebert</hi> the Kingdom (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept out of <hi>Hampſhire</hi>) and he reigned in his ſtead. Almoſt the ſame relation is in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Annals. <hi>Kineulfus, Weſt-Saxonum primatibus adjutus Sigeberti reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num pro malefactis ſuis totum quidem, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptâ Hamtonenſium provinia, occupavit. Kineulf,</hi> by the help of the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Nobility, uſurped or poſſeſt himſelf of <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s whole Kingdom for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, except <hi>Hampſhire</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Saxon.</hi> Chron. <hi>A.</hi> D. 755.</note>. Whence <hi>Kineulf</hi> is alſo derived from <hi>Cerdic,</hi> the Founder of the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Kingdom. This was in the time of the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> when the petty Kings, Earls, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to his Government, took all Opportunities and Pretences to deſtroy and overturn one another. And it was the Action and Contrivance of <hi>Kineulf,</hi> aſſiſted by the rebellious and mutinous Subjects of <hi>Sigebert,</hi> that thruſt him out of his Kingdom. <hi>Malmsbury</hi> hath it thus, <hi>Arripuit regnum Sigebertus, vir apud ſuos ſaevitiâ immanis, idemque foris ignavia perin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famis; quocirca omnium odio conſpirante, poſt annum Solio deturbatus, meliori lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum fecit.</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>n.</hi> 20.30.</note> 
                     <hi>Suſcepit regni gubernacula Kienulphus, clarus &amp; ille quidem morum compoſitione, militiaeque geſtis. Sigebert</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded, or ſeized the Throne, a man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cruel at home, and abroad very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for Sloth and Cowardiſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was hated of all Men, and after one Year being dethroned, made way for a better. <hi>Kineulf,</hi> famous for his good Temper and Military Actions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook the Government. In theſe three moſt Authentick and Ancient Hiſtories there is nothing of a <hi>Convention</hi> of the <hi>Nobles</hi> and People, or an <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neulf,</hi> but they affirm, that both he and <hi>Sigebert,</hi> whom he dethroned, invaded the Government by Force or Fraud, and entered upon it by indirect means; and by ſuch it was to be kept; and for that reaſon the People hated <hi>Sige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Kingdom of</hi> Mercia, Beornredus <hi>for not governing by the Laws, was by a</hi> Convention <hi>of the Nobility and People ſet aſide from the Government, and</hi> Offa <hi>choſen King, who was of the Royal Stem, but not the next Heir: and ſo</hi> William <hi>of</hi> Malmsb. <hi>obſerves, in the</hi> Weſt Saxon Kingdom <hi>after</hi> Ina, <hi>That no Lineal Succeſſion was then obſerved, but ſtill ſome of the Royal Line ſat in the Throne; and of</hi> Ina <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he was rather put into the Throne for his Virtue, than by his Right of Succeſſion.</hi> This Paragraph he makes good by the three parcels of Hiſtory there noted<note place="margin">
                     <p>A. D. <hi>758.</hi> Gensde reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Mercio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, contra Regem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Beornredum inſurgens, pro eo quod populum non aequis legibus, ſed per tyrannidem gubernaret, convenerant in unum omnes, tam Nobiles, quam ignobiles, &amp; Offâ Duce ipſum a regno expulerunt. Mat. Weſt.</p>
                     <p>Nam &amp; ipſe Brithricus &amp; caeteri infra Inam reges, licet Natalium ſplendore gloriantes (quippe qui de Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio originem traherent) non parum tamen a linea re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giae Stirpis exorbitaverant Will. Malmſ. degeſt. Reg. Ang. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Regnum per Inam novatum qui Cinegiſſi ex fratre Cuthhalbo pronepos magis pro inſitivae virtutis induſtriâ, quam ſuceſſivae ſobolis proſapiâ in principatum aſcitur. id. ib.</p>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>What he ſays of <hi>Beornredus</hi> and <hi>Offa</hi> is to be found in <hi>Mat. Weſt.</hi> but nothing to that purpoſe in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology. All that is there to be found of them as to this particular is in <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 755. toward the latter end of the Year. <hi>Eodem anno Aethelbaldus Rex Merciorum Secan-dunae occiſſus eſt; Bearnredus autem regnum capeſſit, &amp; aliquantiſper tenuit. Eodemque anno Rex-Offa regnum ſuſcepit, annoſque triginta &amp; novem tenuit.</hi> In the Year 755. <hi>Ethelbald</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians</hi> was killed at <hi>Secandune,</hi> and <hi>Beornredus</hi> poſſeſſed the Kingdom, and held it a ſmall time. And the ſame Year King <hi>Offa</hi> took the Kingdom, and held it 39. Years. Nor in <hi>Florence</hi> of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> he only ſays, <hi>Rex Merciorum Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelbaldus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59535:4"/> in Segeſwald occiditur; cujus regnum Beoruredus tyrannus invaſit, &amp; per modicum tempus in parvà letitiâ tenens regnum cum vitâ perdidit; quô mortuô ſucceſſit in regnum Nepos patruelis Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldi Regis Merciorum Offa.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">A. D. <hi>755.</hi> f. <hi>574.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ethelbald</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians</hi> was killed in <hi>Segeſwald (i. e. Secandunt)</hi> whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>Beornred</hi> the Tyrant invaded, and holding it a little while with ſmall joy, loſt both the Kingdom and his own Life; and <hi>Offa</hi> the Brothers Son of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelbald</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians</hi> ſucceeded him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Aethelbald,</hi> ſays, <hi>Hic altâ pace, &amp; multo tempore, id eſt Quadraginta uno Annis rerum perfunctus, &amp; noviſſimè a Subjectis occiſus, fortunae ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam volvit, author ejus necis Bernredus nil memorabile dedit, niſi, quod mox ab Offâ necatus, dignum finem Inſidiarum tulit.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">fol. <hi>14.</hi> b. n. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aethelbald</hi> managed his Affairs in a full Peace One and forty Years, but at laſt the Wheel of Fortune turned, and he was killed by his Subjects; the Author of his Death, <hi>Bernred,</hi> left no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing memorable behind him, unleſs his being killed by <hi>Offa,</hi> and thereby receiving a worthy Reward of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</p>
               <p>In theſe Hiſtorians here is <hi>nothing of a Convention,</hi> that either ſet aſide <hi>Beornred,</hi> and choſe <hi>Offa</hi> for their King; but only that <hi>Beornred</hi> was a Tyrant and Traytor, who with his Accomplices murder'd his peaceful Soveraign <hi>Aethelbald,</hi> who in great quiet had govern'd his Kingdom one and forty years, which he invaded and ſet up himſelf, and that <hi>Offa</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged his Uncle <hi>Aethelbald</hi>'s Murder, killed <hi>Bernred,</hi> and ſucceeded in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nment; and doubtleſs by the means of the power and force with which he ſubdued <hi>Bernred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other two parcels of Hiſtory are not fairly cited, or duly placed and laid together; for the Author hath placed that laſt, which is firſt mentioned in the Hiſtorian; and by theſe he would prove, That in the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kingdom after <hi>Ina</hi> no lineal Succeſſion was then obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and <hi>of Ina</hi> himſelf, that he was rather put into the Throne for his Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, than by right of Succeſſion.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>The words of the Hiſtorian are<note n="*" place="margin">Malmſ. degeſt. Reg. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> f. <hi>7.</hi> a. lin. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note>; <hi>Eo Roman eunte Regnum per Inam novatum,</hi> (and ſo on, as cited by the Author) he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rome</hi> (that is, King <hi>Ceadwalla,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom the preceding Diſcourſe had been) <hi>Ina</hi> ſeized upon the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or changed the Succeſſion, who was the Grandchild of <hi>Cuthbald,</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Kinegils,</hi> and was called to the government more for his real Virtue, than by ſucceſſive Birthright.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology<note n="†" place="margin">A. D. <hi>689.</hi>
                     </note> thus expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his coming to the Government; <hi>Ine Feng to Weſt-Seaxna Rice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ina Weſt-Saxonum regnum capeſcit, Eodem anno Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walla Romam Profectus eſt, Baptiſmumque à Papa ſuſcepit, Quem Papa Petrum cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minavit, atque circiter Septimanam unam poſtea defunctus eſt. Ina</hi> took upon him the Government of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>&amp;c. Flor.</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> thus:<note place="margin">A. D. <hi>688.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unte Ceadwalla Romam, ſuſcepit Imperium Ina de ſtirpe Regia; cujus pater Kenre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, cujus pater Ceolwaldus, cujus pater Cutha, cujus pater Cuthwinus, cujus pater Ceanlinus. Ceadwall</hi> going to <hi>Rome, Ina</hi> undertook, or put himſelf upon the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, whoſe Father was <hi>Kenred,</hi> whoſe Father was <hi>Ceoldwald,</hi> whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Cutha,</hi> (or according to <hi>Malmsb. Cuth-bald</hi>) whoſe Father was <hi>Cuthwin,</hi> whoſe Father was <hi>Ceanlin.</hi> In theſe Hiſtories there is nothing how he aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Throne, whether he was called to it, or otherwiſe placed himſelf upon it; or received it, as recommended to it by his Predeceſſour <hi>Ceadwald,</hi> as he himſelf when he went to <hi>Rome</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Succeſſour <hi>Aethelhard. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licto Imperio ac</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Flor. Wig. A. D. <hi>728.</hi> f. <hi>572.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Aethelhardo de proſapiâ Cerdici Regis oriundo, commendato Rex Ina ad limina beatorum Apoſtolorum profectus eſt. Ina</hi> left his Government, and having recommended <hi>Aethelhard,</hi> went to <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology only ſays,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59535:5"/>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">A.D. <hi>728.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ina Romam abiit, ibique Spiritum effla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit; &amp; Aethelhardus Weſt-Saxonum regnum capeſſit, tenuitque annos quatuordecim.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">f. <hi>7.</hi> b. n. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Malmsbury's</hi> words are; <hi>Succeſſit Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatui Aedelardus Inae conſanguineus, per quatuordecim annos quietiſſimè regnum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentum Cuthredo cognato reliquit. Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard</hi> the Kinſman of <hi>Ina</hi> ſucceeded in the Government, enjoyed it quietly four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years, and left it to his Kinſman <hi>Cuthred,</hi> who held it about the like time. In the <hi>Saxon</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">A.D. <hi>741.</hi>
                     </note> Chronology and <hi>Flor.</hi> of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> 'tis, <hi>Cuthred</hi> took upon him the Government, or ſucceeded in the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>The two next Rulers after <hi>Cuthred,</hi> were <hi>Sigebert</hi> and <hi>Kineulf,</hi> of whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brithric</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Kineulf,</hi> but how, and when, none of theſe three Hiſtorians tell us. In his Story we meet with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's laſt parcel of Hiſtory, but very partially cited. They all report, that he married the Daughter of <hi>Offa</hi> King of <hi>Mercia,</hi> at that time moſt potent,<note n="†" place="margin">Malmſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> f. <hi>8.</hi> a. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>cujus affinitate fultus, Egbertum ſolum Regalis Proſapiae Superſtitem, quem validiſſimum ſuis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitatibus metuebat, Obicem Franciam fugandum curavit: nam &amp; ipſe Brithricus, &amp; caeteri infra Inam Reges, licet Natalium ſplendore gloriantes (quippe qui de Cerdicio originem traherent) non parum tamen alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ regiae ſtirpis exorbitaverant: illo igitur expulſo ſecuro reſolvi coeperat otio,</hi> &amp;c. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Affinity of <hi>Offa,</hi> he cauſed <hi>Egbert,</hi> the only Survivor of the Royal Race, to fly into <hi>France,</hi> fearing he would be a great check to his Affairs: for <hi>Brith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric</hi> himſelf, and the other Kings ſince <hi>Ina,</hi> altho they might glory in the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of their Births (as deriving their Origin from <hi>Cerdic</hi>) yet they were not a little out of the way from the line of the Royal Progeny: When <hi>Egbert</hi> was expelled the Kingdom, he began to live ſecurely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From this Obſervation of <hi>Malmsbury</hi>'s, as the Author calls it (if it be one) the lineal Succeſſion before <hi>Ina</hi> (which might be here ſet forth, if needful) is as much proved as no lineal Succeſſion after him; and notwithſtanding the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Uſurpations that had been between the Reign of <hi>Ceadwally,</hi> or <hi>Ina,</hi> and <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who was much feared by <hi>Brithric,</hi> as being the only Survivor, and of right Succeſſor of the Royal Line, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baniſhed into <hi>France;</hi> the lineal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kingdom, was in time revived and continued in the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Monarchy which he founded, as will appear in the further Enquiry into (the Author's) other <hi>Saxon</hi> Inſtances. This if it had been fairly cited, could not have been uſeful to him; but he took what ſerved his turn, and left out the reſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Words of the Author, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aethelulphus,</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> went to <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. Weſt. A. D. <hi>854. 867.</hi>
                  </note> and there crowned <hi>Alfred</hi> his youngeſt Son King; and married the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Daughter, in his return, and made her Queen againſt the Laws; for which reaſon he was excluded his Kingdom, his eldeſt <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Alſton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Shire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> being at the top of this Act of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; and he came back only upon the terms of receiving his Son into a Share of the Kingdom; which ſhews that they looked on the Laws as the meaſure of Allegiance: and where thoſe were openly broken, that it was in their power to transfer it.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex Occidentalium Saxonum Aethelul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus cum honore maximo Romam profectus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Aethelulphus</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons</hi> went with great honour to <hi>Rome,</hi> carrying with him his younger Son <hi>Alfred,</hi> whom he loved beyond all his other Sons, that he might be inſtructed by <hi>Pope Leo</hi> in Manners and Religion, where he ſtay'd a year with his Son, and cauſed him to be crowned King by the <hi>Pope;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter few days returning to his Country, he brought with him <hi>Judith,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> whom he had married. But in the mean time, while the King was beyond Sea, there was a Conſpiracy of certain great Men
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59535:5"/> formed againſt him; the chief of the Conſpiracy were <hi>Aethelbald</hi> his eldeſt Son, and <hi>Alſton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Shireburn,</hi> and <hi>Landulph</hi> Earl of <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> who had reſolved, that upon his return he ſhould never be received to the Government; for which they had two cauſes; One, for that he had cauſed his younger Son <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred</hi> to be crowned at <hi>Rome,</hi> and poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon'd and excluded his other Sons; the ſecond was, That he had deſpiſed all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Women, and married a Stranger. Moreover, the Conſpirators had heard, that contrary to the Cuſtom and Statutes of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings, he called the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Daughter, whom he had lately married, Queen; and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to ſit by him at the Table, and eat with him; which the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Nation did not permit, nor that ſhe ſhould be called Queen, but the King's Wife. <hi>Haec autem infamia ab Eadburga Offae Regis filiâ, ejuſdem generis reginâ, exorta eſt: Quae Virum ſuum Brithricum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eneno perdidit,</hi> &amp;c. The occaſion of which non permiſſion aroſe from <hi>Eadburg</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Offa,</hi> a Queen of the ſame ſort, who deſtroyed her Husband with Poyſon, and ſitting by the King, was wont to accuſe all the Noblemen of the Kingdom; and thoſe ſhe could not accuſe, ſhe killed by Poyſon. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the lewdneſs of the Queen, all conſpired that they would never permit a King to reign over them, <hi>Qui in praedictis culpabilis inveniretur,</hi> who ſhould be found culpable in what hath been ſaid. <hi>Revertente tandem a Roma Aethelulfo Rege Pacifico, praedictus filius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Aethelbaldus, conceptam nequitiam ad effectum producere attentavit; ſed Deus omnipotens id fieri non permiſit,</hi> &amp;c. When the peaceable King <hi>Aethelulph</hi> return'd from <hi>Rome,</hi> his Son <hi>Aethelbald</hi> attempted to effect his wicked Contrivance; but God would not permit it: for to prevent a more than Civil War between Father and Son, by the ineffable Clemency of the King, the Confederacy of all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Biſhops was broken, he dividing the Kingdom of the <hi>Weſt Saxons</hi> between himſelf and Son, which before was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided, ſo as his Son poſſeſſed the Eaſt part, and the Father the Weſt part; <hi>Et cum tota regni Nobilitas pro Rege decertare, &amp; filium a Jure regni depellere vellent, ſi Pater id fieri permiſiſſet, ipſe mentis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate ab avaritiae ſeſe vitio excludens, filii ſui concupiſcentiae ſatisfecit ſicque ubi <hi>Pater juſto Dei Iudicio regnare debuerat, illic filius pertinax &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquus regnavit;</hi>
                     </hi> and when as the whole Nobility of the Kingdom would have fought for the King, and forced his Son from the right of the Kingdom, if his Father would have permitted it to be done; but he being free from all Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, ſatisfied the unruly Appetite of his Son; and ſo where the Father ought to have reigned by the juſt Sentence of God, the obſtinate and wicked Son reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This Story <hi>Mat. Weſtm.</hi> had from <hi>Flor.</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">A. D. <hi>675.</hi>
                     </note>, tho it is not in the laſt altogether ſo formal.<note n="*" place="margin">f. <hi>21.</hi> b. n. <hi>50.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> a. n. <hi>10. 20.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Malmsbury</hi> likewiſe hath it, tho not intirely. But the <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology hath nothing of it, nay rather it hath ſomething contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it.<note n="*" place="margin">A. D. <hi>854.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eodem anno Aethelwulfus rex magno cum honore Romam perrexit, ibique per Menſes Duodecim moratus eſt, cui mox domum redeunti Carolus Francorum Rex filiam ſuam in Reginam dedit; hinc poſteà ad populum ſuum reverſus eſt, qui mirificè laetabatur: ſed poſt biennium, ex quo a Francis redierat, defunctus eſt, corpus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Wintoniae ſepultum jacet.</hi> In the Year 854. <hi>Aethelwulph</hi> went in great Pomp to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he ſtaid Twelve Months. To whom, as he returned home, <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> gave him his Daughter for his Queen: Afterwards, when he returned to his People they rejoyced wonderfully; within Two Years after he died, and his Body lies buried at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> Not one Word here, or any where elſe in this Chronology, of this improbable and Romantick Story. But be it true, as it is told in <hi>Mat. Weſtminſter,</hi> was it againſt their Laws (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>West Saxon</hi> Laws) for <hi>Aethelwulph</hi> to marry the King of <hi>France</hi> his Daughter, and make her his Queen? Where is this Law? It is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59535:6"/> not amongſt <hi>Ina</hi>'s Laws. But the Law was made in <hi>Brithric's</hi> time, by reaſon of the wickedneſs of his Queen <hi>Eadburgh.</hi> If ſhe was as wicked as the Story makes her, was the Anger and Humour of the People againſt her, ſufficient to make a Law, That for the time coming no <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> King ſhould permit his Wife to ſit and eat with him, or be called Queen? Why was ſhe not put to death for her tranſcendent Wickedneſs, if true? Why was ſhe permitted to go into <hi>France,</hi> with innumerable Treaſure after her Husband's death? If there was ſuch a Law made then, 'twas in the time of the <hi>Heptarchy.</hi> Can any Man think that <hi>Egbert</hi> the firſt <hi>Saxon</hi> Monarch did not ſuffer his Wife to ſit and eat with him, and to be called Queen? And that our <hi>Aethelwulph,</hi> who had Four Sons by a former Wife, did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to ſit and eat with him, and to be called Queen? There was a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and wicked Deſign of <hi>Aethelbald</hi> to dethrone his Father, carried on by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Shireburn,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> &amp;c. the pretence was, for that he had cauſed his youngeſt Son <hi>Alfred</hi> to be crowned at <hi>Rome.</hi> What Laws had <hi>Aethelwulph</hi> broken in this, except the Laws of Birth-right, Lineal Deſcent, and Proximity of Blood? Upon which the Succeſſion of the Monarchy was fixed, if <hi>Alſtan, Ethelbald,</hi> or the Earl of <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> underſtood any thing of it. Nor could there be any Excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Aethelwulph,</hi> when the whole Nobility offered to fight for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him; nor could there be any Terms of receiving his Son into a ſhare of the Kingdom, when out of ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Clemency he himſelf divided it, to avoid a Civil War, and would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Nobility to force his Son from the Right of the Kingdom. What right was this? Was it not from Proximity of Blood, and Lineal Succeſſion, he being his eldeſt Son?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>If our Allegiance cannot be transferred by the States of the Realm; it muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, (as ſome think) by the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſtitution of this Kingdom, we are bound in <hi>Allegiance</hi> to <hi>the next Right Heir in a Lineal Succceſſion.</hi> But I find no ſuch thing in the <hi>Saxon</hi> times; for altho they generally kept to the <hi>Royal Line,</hi> yet not ſo, but that when it appeared to be much more for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> they did not ſtick upon the Point of <hi>Proximity.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be oppoſed to the Words and Aſſertion of the Author.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe, who in theſe caſes our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and all others that have written upon this, or the like Subject, do call the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Realm,</hi> and what is due to the Heir in a <hi>Lineal Succeſſion</hi> by the Laws of our Land, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Conſtitution of the Kingdom, ſhall be conſider'd afterwards. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Saxon</hi> Succeſſion, what hath been already ſaid might be ſufficient; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on further occaſion given in his Inſtances, there will be more ſaid of it. The <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good,</hi> which the Author here, and in many other places, ſeems to rely mainly upon to ſupport what he aſſerts, is chiefly to be enquired after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publick</hi> or <hi>Common Good</hi> is a common Notion, and ſignifies nothing unleſs it be ſtated, and explain'd; the true import of the Words are, That every Individual of the common Body, according to the capacity of the Perſon, ſhould and ought to be made a partaker of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and advantage that ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to the whole; for if it be ſuch a Good, (or rather ſuch an Evil) as is only for the benefit of a Party, and in reſpect of the whole, of the leaſt, or a ſmall number; 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be a <hi>Publick Good,</hi> but a moſt horrid cheat put upon the People under that pretence, to gull them into Slavery, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59535:6"/> to make them the Authors of their own, and the <hi>Publick Ruin</hi> of the <hi>Nation.</hi> All deſigning Men of whatſoever Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though if called together, cannot ſay what they would have; yet in all Ages have pretended to procure the <hi>Publick Good</hi> of the People. Every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (though in the beginning never ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable) that intends to advance it ſelf, declares for it until it gets Power to manage, and appropriate to themſelves what they call ſo; and then it appears the Intereſt, Gain, and Advancement of the Party were the End; and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Common Good,</hi> but the Means to that End. And this pretence, and falſe light, hath at all times ſo Lowbell'd the blind and ignorant World, that Men fly into the Net, though they ſee all the Laws broken that maintain the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> and the very Foundations of it eradicated; all the goodly Pretences and fair Promiſes relinquiſht, and utter deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation coming upon them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where it is manifeſt the Publick Laws are, or cannot but be broken, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, and vilified by any Party, 'tis <hi>Private and Party-Good</hi> they only intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and to accompliſh their ends, and ſecure themſelves, muſt proceed againſt all the Meaſures and Rules of <hi>Publick Good,</hi> by fraud, force, and violence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſtupendious Devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For nothing can be a <hi>Publick Good</hi> to any Nation, where the exerciſe and practice of it is not warranted by the Law, Cuſtom and Conſtitution of that Nation. So that the Authors Argument, upon the account of <hi>Common Good,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies little, unleſs he can prove the <hi>Saxons</hi> waved Proximity of Blood; and that they did it according to the Law and Conſtitution of the Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 101. <hi>Brompton</hi> p. 862. l. 1. c. 3. p. 14.</note>
                  <hi>I ſhall not meddle with the Kingdom of the</hi> Northumbers, <hi>which alone was</hi> Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Elective, <hi>as appears by</hi> Mat. Weſtm. <hi>and wherein there happened ſo great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and Confuſions, that at laſt</hi> William <hi>of</hi> Malmsb. <hi>ſaith,</hi> none could be perſwaded to accept of the Kingdom.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Regnum Northanhumbrorum exordium ſumpſit.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>M. Weſtm. A. D.</hi> 548. f. 101. n. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Cùm enim Proceres Anglorum magnis laboribus &amp; continuis Patriam illam ſubjugâſſent, Idam juvenem Nobiliſſimum Regem ſibi unanimiter praefecerunt.</hi> In the year 548 the Kingdom of the <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> firſt began. The chief Men, or Leaders of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd that Country, unanimouſly ſet up <hi>Ida,</hi> a moſt noble young Man, for their King. What if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Kingdom of the <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> did ſet up <hi>Ida</hi> (in all probability at that time the great Leader of them) to be their King? Doth it therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that Kingdom was Elective, or that they choſe their King afterward?<note place="margin">A. D. <hi>547</hi>
                     </note> The <hi>Saxon</hi> Chronology ſays only, <hi>Ida caepit regnare, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Northanhymbrenſium Genus Regale ortum eſt.</hi> In the year 547. <hi>Ida</hi> began to Reign, from whom aroſe the Royal Race of the <hi>Northumbers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eod Anno.</note> 
                     <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſays, <hi>In provincia Berni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum Ida regnum ſuſcepit, &amp;</hi> 12 <hi>annis reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit; hic ex Reginis ſex filios habuit, &amp; ſex habuit ex Pellicibus. Ex Quibus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis Northanhymbrorum proſapia propagata eſt.</hi> In the Province of <hi>Bernicia</hi> (part of the Kingdom of <hi>Northumberland) Ida</hi> took the Kingdom. He had ſix Sons by his Queens, and as many by his Harlots; from whom the Royal Stock was propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated. <hi>Malmsbury</hi> ſays, <hi>Ida</hi> Reigned the firſt in the Kingdom of <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fol. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> n. 40.</note> but whether he made himſelf King, <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum atrum ipſe per ſe Principatum invaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> or took it by the conſent of others, he could not define, <hi>parum definio quid Veritas in abdito eſt.</hi> In <hi>Brompton,</hi> whom he cites in the Margent, there is <hi>nothing</hi> to be found of an <hi>Election,</hi> but only that the <hi>Northumbers</hi> tumultuouſly ſet up ſome Kings, and Murther'd and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned others; which was a common Practice in moſt Kingdoms during the <hi>Saxon</hi> Heptarchy; and the ſame Reaſon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59535:7"/> the Author gives, that he would not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with this Kingdom, might have been given for the paſſing by all the other, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Kingdom of the <hi>Weſt Saxons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if by the Fundamental Conſtitution,</hi> Allegiance <hi>were indiſpenſably due to the next</hi> Rightful Heir <hi>in this Monarchy, how came</hi> Aethelſian <hi>to be Crowned</hi> magno conſenſu Optimatum, <hi>ſays</hi> Malmsbury, <hi>when he was not the rightful Heir?</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lor. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rn. A D. <hi>24. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>2.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Invictiſſimus rex Edwardus ſenior ex hâc vitâ tranſiens Aethelſtano filio regni gubernacula reliquit; nec multo poſt filius ejus Aelfwardus (alias Edwardus) apud Oxenfordam deceſſit, &amp; ſepultus eſt ubi &amp; pater illius. Aethelſtanus vero in Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtune,</hi> i. e. <hi>in Regiâ Villâ, in regem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levatur, &amp; honorificie ab Athelmo, Dorober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi Archiepiſcopo, conſecratur.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible King <hi>Edward</hi> the Elder, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of this World, left the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his Kingdom to his Son <hi>Aethelſtan;</hi> and not long after him, his Son <hi>Aelward</hi> (or <hi>Edward</hi>) died at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and was buried where his Father was; but, or then, <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> was ſaluted King, and was honourably Conſecrated or Anointed and Crowned by <hi>Athelm</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> at <hi>Kingſton. Anno Dominicae Incarnationis</hi> 924.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lms.</hi> f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. n. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanus filius Edwardi regnare coepit, frater ejus Ethelwardus (alias Edwardus) pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis diebus poſt patrem vita decedens, ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam cum eodem Wintoniae meruerat.</hi> This is what <hi>Florence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſays, and needs no Tranſlation.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dem.</note> 
                     <hi>Itaque magno conſenſu optimatum Electus, apud Regiam villam, Quae vocatur Kingſton Coronatus.</hi> Therefore being Elected, or Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by full conſent of the Great Men, he was Crowned at <hi>Kingſton;</hi> and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Place,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. f. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 30. <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 84. n.</note> 
                     <hi>Poſt mortem Patris, &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritum Fratris, in Regem apud Kingſton coronatus eſt. Anno. Gratiae</hi> 924. <hi>Rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum Edwardus cognomento ſenior diem clauſit extremum, Aethelſtanus quoque filius ejus primogenitus, apud Kingſtonam rex cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus, ab Athelmo Dorobernenſi Archiepiſcopo conſecratur.</hi> Here <hi>Mat. Weſtm.</hi> ſays, <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelſtan</hi> was King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Eldeſt Son, which was true after his Brother was dead. If the Author had taken notice of theſe Hiſtorians, eſpecially of <hi>Malms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> whom he cites, he would have known how <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> came to be <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heir.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Authors words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>Some ſay (from an old Monk in <hi>Malms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury) that his Father left him his Crown by his Teſtament;</hi> (which doth not clear the difficulty, as to the inviolable right of <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> by the <hi>Conſtitution</hi>) But this cannot be true, for his Elder Brother <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> died after his Father, and none pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that his Father diſinherited him.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Hiſtory and Inquiry into theſe Words.</head>
                  <p>A pretty Story. This old Monk in <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> was <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> himſelf (whom he cited but two Lines before) <hi>Juſſu Patris in Teſtamento Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanus in Regem acclamatus eſt.</hi> This the Hiſtorian ſays of himſelf, without vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any old Monk for it. By the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Father in his Teſtament, <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> was Proclaimed or Saluted King. Which clears the difficulty about <hi>Election,</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> having power to diſpoſe of the Crown. As to the truth of it, no body can doubt, that obſerves what is ſaid before of his Elder Brother <hi>Edward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>And if <hi>Athelſtan</hi> was <hi>Lawful Heir,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. Weſtm. A. D. <hi>934.</hi> A. D. <hi>939.</hi>
                  </note> what made him to diſpatch his Brother <hi>Edwin</hi> out of the way, and to build two Monaſtries for expiation of that Guilt?</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59535:7"/>
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Florence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> hath nothing of this <hi>Idle Story;</hi> and <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> from whom <hi>Matt. Weſtminſter</hi> tranſcribed the very words of it (and added ſomething of his own) did not believe it, and tells it as a <hi>Fable;</hi> but before he begins it, he Apologizes for telling it; and after he had reported the Deſign, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of <hi>Alfred</hi> againſt King <hi>Athelſtan,</hi> who would have made him a Baſtard, and ſo kept him from the Throne, ſaith thus, <hi>Et haec quidem fide integra de rege conſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Malmg.</hi> f. 29 <hi>a.</hi> n. 10, l. 2. c. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>ſequentia magis Cantilenis per Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones temporum detritis, quam libri ad Inſtitutiones poſterorum elucubratis didicerim. Quae ideo appoſui, non ut earum veritatem defendam, ſed ne Lectorum ſcientiam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraudem, ac primum de Nativitate dicendum.</hi> And theſe things I have written concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King, may intirely be believed. Thoſe which follow, I rather learnt from old Songs and Tales, then Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for the Information of Poſterity, which I have inſerted here,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> n. 20, 30, 40.</note> 
                     <hi>not that I ſhall defend the truth</hi> of them, but that I may not keep from the Readers what is to be known; and then proceeds to tell a Romantick Prodigy of a Shepherds Beautiful Daughter, out of whoſe Womb a Moon ſhone, that irradiated all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. With this Virgin <hi>Edward</hi> the Elder ſtole a leap, by the aſſiſtance of his ſometime Nurſe, and upon the firſt Enjoyment of her, begat <hi>Aethelſtan,</hi> &amp;c. And goes on to tell, <hi>Edwin</hi> his Brother was accuſed by ſome to have been in the Conſpiracy with <hi>Alfred,</hi> and for that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, out of Jealouſly, he was by order of <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> put into a ſmall Pinnace, without either Tackle, or Oars, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied only with one Page, with grief whereof he leaped into the Sea and drowned himſelf. After this he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſubjoyns; <hi>Haec de fratris nece, etſi veriſimilia videantur, eò minùs corrobero, quod mirabilem ſuae pietatis diligentiam in reliquos fratres intenderet. Quos cum pater pueros admodum reliquiſſet, ille parvos magnâ dulcedine fovit, &amp; adultos regni conſortes fecit.</hi> Although theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the death of his Brother may ſeem probable, yet I eſteem them leſs firm, by reaſon of the admirable Piety he ſhew'd towards his other Brothers; whom he cheriſht with great kindneſs, when his Father left them very Children; and when they were grown up, made them ſharers in the Government. Not one word in <hi>Malmsbury</hi> of <hi>Athelſtan</hi>'s building two Monaſteries, to expiate the Guilt of <hi>Edwin</hi>'s murder. This was <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>'s own.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>How came <hi>Alfred</hi> to oppoſe his Election, <hi>as being Illegitimate,</hi> as <hi>Malmsbury</hi> confeſſes?</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He alſo confeſſes,</hi> That Alfred and his Complices were factious People, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported he was born of a Concubine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Malmsb.</hi> l. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 10.</note> to obviate his being Crowned; and that Sedition ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wants Abettors. Aethelſtanus apua Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia villa quae vocatur Kingſton coronatus, quamvis Quidam Alfredus cum factioſis ſuis, (quia ſeditio ſemper invenit complices) obviare tentâſſet: occaſio contradictionis, ut ferunt. quod Aethelſtanus ex Concubinâ na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſſet; <hi>and in another place, King</hi> Edward <hi>and his Son</hi> Elward,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>or</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>being dead,</hi> Tunc omnium ſpebus in Ethelſtanum erectis; ſolus Alfredus magnae inſolentiae homo cum ſuis clam reſtitit quoad potuit, dedignatus ſubdi Domino, quem ſuo non delegiſſet arbitrio. <hi>Then all Mens hopes were placed upon</hi> Ethelſtan, <hi>only</hi> Alfred <hi>a Man of great inſolence, and his Party oppoſed him, diſdaining to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to a Governour, that he himſelf had not ſet up.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> Mat. Weſtm. <hi>gives the Reaſon:</hi> The times were then difficult, and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> other Sons were too young to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59535:8"/> the Government, and therefore they ſet up <hi>Athelſtan,</hi> as one fit for Buſineſs.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mat. Weſtm.</hi> tranſcribes many of the Words of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> in the place laſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but leaves out that Clauſe of <hi>Alfred</hi>'s being an Inſolent Man, and his making oppoſition to <hi>Athelſtan;</hi> and adds this of his own,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>A. D.</hi> 934. f 186. n. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Spreto Edwino, nondum ad regnandum propter teneros annos idoneo, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelſtanum in Kingſtonâ conſecravêrunt.</hi> From the partial Conſtruction and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of theſe laſt Words above what they will bear, the Author hath ſet up a particular Senſe of his own, againſt the Senſe and Report of all other Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; nay, againſt the Report of <hi>M. Weſtm.</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>A. D.</hi> 924.</note> who ſays, <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> was made King, and Crowned as <hi>Edward</hi>'s eldeſt Son.</p>
                  <p>After the Death of <hi>Aethelſtan,</hi> his own Author ſays,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>M. Weſtm. A. D.</hi> 940. f. 187. lin. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Succeſſit ei in regnum frater ejus, &amp; haeres legitimus Eadmundus.</hi> His Brother, and lawful Heir, <hi>Edmaend</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>How came <hi>Edred</hi> to ſucceed <hi>Edmund,</hi> and not his own Sons <hi>Edwin,</hi> and <hi>Edgar? Mat. Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>Brompton</hi> give the ſame Reaſon,<note place="margin">M. Weſtm. A. <hi>946.</hi> Brompt. <hi>p. 862.</hi> Flor. Wig. A. <hi>949.</hi>
                  </note> They were uncapable by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Age: <hi>Repugnance illegitimâ aetate patri ſuccedere non valebant. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſaith, The <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> ſware Allegiance to <hi>Edred;</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>He was next Heir;</hi> and yet there were two Sons of <hi>Edmond</hi> before him; for he confeſſes, that they were the Sons of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> and <hi>Algiva</hi> his Queen.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>M. Weſtm.</hi> f. 188. n. 30.</note>
                     <hi>Defuncto Edmundo &amp; apud Glaſtoniam ſepulto, Eadredus frater ejus, in Kingſtona regiâ villâ, regni diadema à B. Othone Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. Cantuarienſi ſuſcepit. Reliquit quoque duos filios, haeredes legitimos, Eadwinum &amp; Eadgarum, qui repugnante illegitima aetate, patri ſuccedere non valebant. Edmund</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, his Brother <hi>Edred</hi> was Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Otho</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> He left alſo two Sons his lawful Heirs, <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Edgar;</hi> who by reaſon of their Non-age, could not ſucceed their Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mortuo Edmundo rege,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Brompton,</hi> col. 862. n. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Edredus frater ſuus, filiuſque Regis Adelſtani, eo quod pueri Edwinus &amp; Edgarus filii Edmundi, pra immaturâ aetate adhuc regnare non poterant, ſibi in Regem ſucceſſit, &amp; ab Odone Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernenſi Archiep. conſecratus eſt,</hi> A. D. 947. <hi>Edmund</hi> being dead <hi>Edred</hi> his Brother, and the Son of King <hi>Athelſtan,</hi> ſucceeded him as King, for that the Children <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Edmund, by reaſon of their tender Age, could not as <hi>yet</hi> reign.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Magnificus rex Anglorum Edmundus die feſtivitatis Sancti Auguſtini, &amp;c. interficitur;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Flor. Wig.</hi> f. 604. <hi>A. D.</hi> 946.</note> 
                     <hi>mox proximus haeres Edredus fratri ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, regnum naturale ſuſcepit, a Sancto Odone, &amp;c.</hi> The Magnificent King <hi>Edmund</hi> was killed on the Feſtival of St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> preſently the next Heir <hi>Edred,</hi> ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Brother, took upon him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment according to Nature, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Natural Duty and Affection.</p>
                  <p>If the Author had fairly and truly ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe Three Pieces of Hiſtory, it had not been impoſſible to have found out that <hi>Edred</hi> was but only Tutor, Curator, Regent, or Protector of the young Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Kingdom; and ſo took upon him the Government, until they were of ſufficient Age. <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſays, <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Edgar were the lawful Heirs of Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> (which Words the Author left out) <hi>but could not ſucceed him by reaſon of their Nonage, or that they were not of lawful Age. Brompton</hi> ſays, Edred <hi>ſucceeded his Brother, for that his Sons</hi> Edwin <hi>and</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, <hi>by reaſon of their immature Age could not <hi>yet</hi> reign.</hi> As much as to ſay, Tho in reſpect of their Age they could not at preſent, yet afterwards in their riper Years they were to reign; and ſo they <hi>did ſucceſſively.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Florence</hi> of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> ſays, Edred <hi>was next Heir.</hi> What Heir could he be to his Brother, but Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolary or Teſtamentary Heir, or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor? (For in that ſenſe <hi>Hares</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59535:8"/> uſed.) And ſo 'twas moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by ſome Inſtrument or other he made him Tutor, Curator, Regent, or Protector of his Sons and Kingdom; or that by Conſent of the Great Men, he took upon him the Tutorſhip, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency. For what other Meaning can thoſe Words have, <hi>regnum naturale ſuſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,</hi> than that according to natural Duty and Affection he took upon him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Protection of his Nephews, and their Kingdom? But how then came it to paſs, that he was Crowned, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led King? 'Tis not hard to anſwer this Queſtion: For anciently the Sons and Heirs of Emperors, Kings, Dukes, Earls, Barons, were not always called ſo; but Heirs only of the Empire, Kingdom, Dukedom,<note place="margin">Du Freſn Gloſſ. vol. <hi>2.</hi> in verb. <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redes,</hi> col. <hi>686, 687.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Tutor, Curator, Governor, or Protector, and ſuch as had the Care of them, and the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government, were then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Emperors, Kings, Dukes, Earls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of ſuch Empires, Kingdoms, Dukedoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until the Heir came of Age; and ſometimes thoſe Curators and Guardian Kings and Emperors were anointed and crowned: But when the Heirs were of lawful Age, they quitted their Curator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Regency, and parted with or laid down all Royal Marks of Majeſty, retaining only the Name and Honour of King: And the Title of King, and the Ceremony of Coronation, was allowed and granted to ſuch Regents, that they might have the greater Authority with the People. Of ſuch Curators, Tutors, or Regents, <hi>Du Freſn</hi> gives ſeveral Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and of <hi>Odo</hi> Duke of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> Tutor to <hi>Charles</hi> the Simple, not much before this time, and of other Kings of <hi>France,</hi> that had Crowned Tutors with the Titles of Kings.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A.</hi> 957.</note>After the Death of <hi>Edred,</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Edmond</hi> ſucceeded; but being found under a <hi>Moral Incapacity</hi> (for in <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> his words, and <hi>M. Weſtminſter, In commiſſo regimine inſipienter egit</hi>) he was ſet aſide, as to all the Government be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Thames,</hi> and <hi>Edgar</hi> put into it.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiit Edredus Rex die S. Clementis fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, in aetatis vigore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chron. Sax. A. D. <hi>955</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>decem circiter annos regnabat, deinceps Eadwigus, Eadmundi Regis filius, regnum capeſſit, &amp; Sanctum Dunſtanum de terrâ fugavit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eadwigus rex Calendis Octobris obiit.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>957.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eadgarus autem frater ejus regnum capeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. Hic Sanctum Dunſtanum accerſit, eique Epiſcopatum Wigornienſem donavit, &amp; poſtea Londinenſem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>King <hi>Edred</hi> died in the Feſtival of St. <hi>Clement,</hi> in the vigor of his Age, after he had reigned about Ten years. Then <hi>Eadwy</hi> the Son of <hi>Edmund</hi> enjoy'd the Kingdom, and baniſh't St. <hi>Dunſtan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eadwy</hi> died the Firſt of <hi>October,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Edgar</hi> took the Kingdom, and recalled St. <hi>Dunſtan,</hi> and gave him the Biſhoprick of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and afterward that of <hi>London.</hi> This Chronology hath not one word of the <hi>Northumbers</hi> and <hi>Mercians</hi> rejecting <hi>Edwy,</hi> and chuſing <hi>Edgar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex Anglorum Eadwigus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Flor. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn. eodem An.</note> 
                     <hi>quoniam in commiſſo regimine inſipienter egit, a Mercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus &amp; Northimbrenſibus contemptus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquitur. &amp; ſuus germanus Clito Eadgarus ab eis rex eligitur, ſicque res Regum ſejun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta eſt, ut flumen Thameſii regnum diſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaret amborum: mox Rex Mercenſium Eadgarns heatum Dunſtanum Abbatem</hi> (then Abbot of <hi>Glaſtenbury) cum honore &amp; gloriâ revocavit.</hi> King <hi>Edwy,</hi> becauſe he acted fooliſhly in his Government, was deſpiſed, and deſerted by the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and <hi>Northumbrians,</hi> and his Brother Prince <hi>Edgar</hi> choſen; and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kings was ſo divided, as the <hi>Thames</hi> bounded both their Kingdoms: and King <hi>Edgar</hi> preſently called back St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi> the Abbot with honour and glory. The Words of <hi>M. Weſtminſter</hi> are moſtly the very ſame, as theſe before-cited; the Senſe differs not. After this, they both tell, how Abbot <hi>Dunſtan</hi> was made, firſt Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> then of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59535:9"/> 
                     <hi>London,</hi> by King <hi>Edgar.</hi> The Author at his firſt entrance upon the <hi>Saxon</hi> Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>p.</hi> 15. ſaid, <hi>he would not meddle with the Kingdom of Northumbers</hi> (which in this place both the Hiſtorians he cites do expreſly mention) for Reaſons there gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and therefore thinking this Inſtance to be for his purpoſe, he cunningly omits to mention that Nation, as believing for his own Reaſons it might undervalue the Inſtance; and only ſays, <hi>Edwy</hi> was ſet aſide as to all the Government beyond <hi>Thames,</hi> and <hi>Edgar</hi> put into it.</p>
                  <p>But what if the <hi>Northumbrians</hi> and <hi>Mercians</hi> did reject him? 'Twas no more than the <hi>Northumbrians</hi> had done in the two preceding Reigns.<note place="margin">Flor. Wig. A. D. <hi>926.</hi>
                     </note> They made a League with <hi>Aethelſtan,</hi> and confirm'd it by Oath; yet they called in <hi>Anlaf</hi> a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan King, and raiſed War againſt him: And tho' he,<note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>937.</hi>
                     </note> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> his Aſſiſtant, and the <hi>Northumbrians</hi> were baffled with great Slaughter of their Men, yet but Four years after, and in the Firſt year of King <hi>Edmund,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>941.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Northimbrenſes fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitati, quam magnifico regi Anglorum Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundo, debebant, infidelitatem praeferentes, Regem Northmannorum Anlafam ſibi in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem eligêrunt.</hi> The <hi>Northumbrians</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Infidelity to the Fealty they ought to the Magnificent King <hi>Edmund,</hi> choſe <hi>Anlaf</hi> King of <hi>Norway</hi> for their King.<note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>944.</hi>
                     </note> Three years after, <hi>Magnificus rex Anglorum Edmundus duos reges Anlafum, Regis videlicet Sithrici filium, &amp; Reignol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Guthfredi filium de Northumbriâ ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulit, eamque ſuae ditioni ſubegit.</hi> King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> drove two Kings, <hi>Anlaf</hi> the Son of <hi>Sithric,</hi> and <hi>Reinold</hi> the Son of <hi>Gutred,</hi> out of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and conquer'd, or reduced it under his Power.<note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>949.</hi>
                     </note> And Five years after that, <hi>Wolſtanus Archiepiſcopus Eboracenſis, procereſque Northimhembrenſes omnes, egregio regi Anglorum Edredo fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem juraverunt, ſed non illam diu tenue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Wulſtan</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and all the Great Men of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> ſware Fealty to the famous King <hi>Edred,</hi> but did not long keep it: <hi>Namque quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Danicâ ſtirpe progenitum (Ircum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine) ſuper ſe Regem levaverunt.</hi> For they ſet up <hi>Iric,</hi> a <hi>Dane,</hi> King over them: And the very next year King <hi>Edred</hi> threatning to deſtroy the whole Country,<note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>950.</hi>
                     </note> they threw down <hi>Iric, (Ircum quem ſibi regem praefecerant abjecêrunt)</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with <hi>Edred</hi> for a great Sum of Money.<note place="margin">Ibid. A. D. <hi>957.</hi>
                     </note> And ſeven years after they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from <hi>Edwin,</hi> and ſet up his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Edgar:</hi> And like them were the <hi>Mercians.</hi> Would any Man fetch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from theſe People, to confirm and warrant what he would prove, or have thought to be a juſt and regular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding?</p>
                  <p>But what was his Crime? How did he play the Fool? Why,<note place="margin">Malmsb. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> f. <hi>30.</hi> a. n. <hi>20. 30.</hi>
                     </note> he baniſht <hi>Dunſtan</hi> Chief of the Monks, turn'd the Monks out of Monaſteries, and put in Secular Prieſts, and made bold with the Monks Revenue: By which Folly he made them his Enemies, and loſt the People, ſo as he could not chaſtiſe the <hi>Northumbrians,</hi> as <hi>Edred</hi> had done before him; and ſo was <hi>forced</hi> to be content to let his Brother <hi>Edgar</hi> enjoy <hi>Mercia</hi> and <hi>Northumberland;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chron. Sax. A. D. <hi>957.</hi>
                     </note> who forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called <hi>Dunſtan</hi> from Exile, and reſtored the Monks, where he could; which made him ſecure againſt his Brother <hi>Edwy,</hi> after whoſe Death he poſſeſt the whole Nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>How came there to be a Diſpute about the Election, after the death of <hi>Edgar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his eldeſt Son <hi>Edward,</hi> and <hi>Etheldred</hi> his youngeſt?</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>Malmsbury <hi>anſwers the Queſtion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> f. <hi>33.</hi> b. n. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardum Dunſtanus &amp; ceteri Epiſcopi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentanci, regali culmine ſublimârunt, contra voluntatem quorundam (ut aiunt) Optima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; Novercae, quae vix Septem annorum puerulum Ethelredum filium, ſuum prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here conabatur, ut ipſa potius ſub ejus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine imperitaret. Dunſtan <hi>and the other Biſhops that agreed with him, ſet</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>in the Throne, againſt the mind
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59535:9"/> (as they ſay) of ſome great Men, and his</hi> Stepmother, <hi>who endeavoured to ſet up her Son</hi> Ethelred, <hi>a Child ſcarce Seven Years old, that under his name ſhe might reign.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>I lay no force upon his Mothers endeavours to advance him; but if there had been ſuch an unalterable Right of Succeſſion, there had not been any colour or pretence for it.</p>
               <p>Tis true, there neither was nor could be any; yet ſhe with her Friends endeavour'd it, and ſeeing ſhe could not do it that way, ſhe afterwards cauſed <hi>Edward</hi> to be murther'd, that the Right of Succeſſion might be in her Son after the Eldeſt was taken away; ſo much the unalterable Right of Succeſſion was then underſtood. But ſaith <hi>Flor. Wig.</hi> there was a great Contention amongſt the great Men about the choice of the King.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A.</hi> 975.</note> How could there be any diſpute if they knew the Conſtitution of the Kingdom to be, that the next Heir muſt inherit the Crown.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Flor. Wig. f. <hi>607.</hi> A. D. <hi>975.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>De rege eligendo magna inter regni pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores oborta eſt diſſentio. Quidam nam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Regis filium Edwardum, quidam autem fratrem illius elegerunt Ethelredum Quam ob cauſam Archipraeſules, Dunſtanus &amp; Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waldus cum Corepiſcopis, Abbatibus, Duci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſque quam plurimis, in unum convenerunt, &amp; Edwardum, ut pater ejus praeciperat, elegerunt, electum conſecraverunt, &amp; in Regem unxerunt.</hi> There was a great Contention amongſt the prime Men of the Kingdom about chooſing, or ſetting up a King. Some were for <hi>Edward,</hi> ſome for <hi>Ethelred;</hi> For which cauſe the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops <hi>Dunſtan</hi> and <hi>Oſwald,</hi> with their Suffragans, the Abbots, and very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Men, aſſembled and choſe <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as his Father had commanded,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated and anointed him King. From what hath been ſaid before, it appears thoſe that would have ſet up <hi>Ethelred</hi> againſt the Right of Succeſſion, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Edward,</hi> King <hi>Edgar</hi>'s eldeſt Son, were his Stepmother and her Party: the others that oppoſed her Deſign, and kept faſt to <hi>Edward,</hi> were for the Right of Succeſſion: with the laſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Conſtitution then was, or the Great Aſſembly of the Nation, that is, the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, and very many Noblemen concurred, and choſe, or recognized and crowned <hi>Edward</hi> their King; whom his Father at his Death <hi>Regni &amp; morum Haeredem reliquit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> left Heir of his Kingdom and Temper. It cannot be thought but this Aſſembly underſtood the Conſtitution of the Nation; and yet there aroſe a diſpute about the Succeſſion. The beſt Laws in the World cannot keep Men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wicked, nor ſecure the Government from the Attempts of Intruders and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers, when they think they have Opportunity and Means to ſet themſelves up, let the Conſtitution be never ſo clear and well known. If the Author would have look'd into, or conſidered the cauſe of this Contention about the Succeſſion, he might as well have asked how can there be any Intruders againſt the known Conſtitution, as how could there be a Diſpute about the Succeſſion? <hi>M. Weſtminſter</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">A. D. <hi>977</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Edward retained on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Name of a King, and by the Flattery of his Stepmother, he permitted to her and her Son</hi> Aethelred <hi>the Tranſaction of all the Affairs of the Kingdom.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. A. D <hi>978.</hi> Flor. Wig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eod Anno.</note> Yet ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a thing, and ſo agreeable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, was Succeſſion by Birth right, that for the eſtabliſhing her Son in the Throne, the very next Year ſhe cauſed <hi>Edward</hi> to be murthered, and triumph'd at his Death.</p>
                  <p>The next are his <hi>Daniſh</hi> Inſtances. Theſe People had the Sword only for their Title, and ſtaid but Five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years or thereabouts: Nor can any Man affirm from our Hiſtorians what the Conſtitution of the Kingdom was then, as to the Government or Governours; and the manner of, and chief pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tence to the Succeſſion, was Donation; as hath been noted before, to which the Reader is referred. <hi>Edmund Ironſide,</hi> the true
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59535:10"/> lineal <hi>Saxon</hi> Heir, made an agreement with <hi>Canutus,</hi> and divided the Kingdom with him, who had no other pretence to the Throne, than his Father <hi>Swane</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and his own Army of <hi>Danes</hi> to make it good. After the Death of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> the Biſhops and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility ſware they would have <hi>Cnute</hi> for their King, would humbly obey him, and pay his Taxes for his Army.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>id. A. D. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>16.</hi> f. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eique humiliter obedire vellent, &amp; ſuo exercitui vectigalia dare.</hi> Let the Author ſay, whether it were not Force and Fear made theſe Men ſwear?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>After the death of <hi>Canutus,</hi> a new dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference aroſe about the Succeſſion;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1055.</note> ſome were for <hi>Harold,</hi> his ſuppoſed Son by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giva;</hi> others for <hi>Hardecnute.</hi> his Son by <hi>Emma.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>After the Death of <hi>Cnute,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>almsb. l. c. <hi>12.</hi> f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. b. n. <hi>50. 43.</hi> a lin. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Elegerûnt Haraldum Dani &amp; Londoniae cives, qui jam penè in Barbacorum mores propter fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem convictum tranſierant. Angli diu obſtiterint, magis unum ex filiis Ethelredi, qui in Normanniâ, vel Hardecnutum filium Cnutonii ex Emma, qui tunc in Danemarchia erat, regem habere volentes.</hi> The <hi>Danes,</hi> and <hi>Citizens</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> who were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt become barbarous by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them, choſe <hi>Harald:</hi> the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> oppoſed, and had rather have had for their King one of the Sons of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelred,</hi> who were then in <hi>Normandy,</hi> or <hi>Hardecnute,</hi> the Son of <hi>Cnute</hi> by <hi>Emme,</hi> who was then in <hi>Danemark,</hi> Earl <hi>Godwin,</hi> who profeſt himſelf Tutor or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator of the Children <hi>(pupillorum Tuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſe profeſſus)</hi> headed the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but at length, being unequal in Force and Number, gave way to violence; <hi>ſed tandem vi &amp; numero impar, cêſſit violentiae.</hi> All Hiſtorians concluded <hi>Harald</hi> to have been a Baſtard; yet without doubt he had a very great Command in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Army, which ſet him up; and it may be with the Aſſiſtance of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Word's, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>If the Lineal Succeſſion were a part of our Conſtitution; how come ſuch perpetual Diſputes to be concerning it? For if it had been own'd as a Fundamental Law, the right of Succeſſion muſt have been clear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond diſpute.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be ſaid to the Reaſoning of the Author.</head>
                  <p>The Author would be thought to have read much Hiſtory; but certainly he never conſidered what he read. Did he in all his reading never meet with U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers, Invaders, and Intruders? Did he never read of Men, that above all things deſired to be Kings, though they knew they had no right to be ſo? Did he never read of the Attempts of ſuch Men to make themſelves ſo; and that ſome have failed, and others ſucceeded in thoſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts? Did he never read, that ſuch Men always had Abbettors, and a Party to carry on their Deſigns? Did he never hear of ſuch wicked Men, as have acted contrary to the light of Nature, and their own Conſciences? or to the great Rule of all Mankind; <hi>Do as you would have others do unto you?</hi> The Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Law of Succeſſion may be as clear, as the light it ſelf; yet Invaders, though they know it, will not ſee it, nor do think themſelves bound by it; but their whole Contrivance is how to evade, baffle, and enervate that Law, and every other Law that ſtands in their way, and yet pretend to advance the <hi>Publick Intereſt,</hi> the <hi>Common Good</hi> of the People, when they intend only to ſet up <hi>their own,</hi> and the Intereſt of the <hi>Party,</hi> againſt the known Laws of the Nation. If theſe things have frequently been, they may be ſo again. 'Tis the Invader, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59535:10"/> Intruder, makes the Diſpute, not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Poſſeſſion by a Lawful Title; he never goes about to quarrel with his own Right and juſt Occupancy; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis not hard to know, how Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes come to be about Lineal Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Though the Right be clear beyond diſpute, Men of deſigns againſt the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Right will take hold of, and make advantage of every opportunity to do their buſineſs.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Words of the Author ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd to his Reaſoning, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>But <hi>reaſon of State,</hi> and the <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> ſtill over-ruled this matter; and ſo <hi>Ethelred</hi>'s Sons by <hi>Emma,</hi> who were the true Heirs by <hi>Legal Succeſſion,</hi> were ſet aſide; and <hi>Harold,</hi> being upon the place, and ſo beſt able to manage the Affairs of the Kingdom, carried it.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be ſaid to the Authors In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from his precedent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning.</head>
                  <p>A fine Piece of Art and Legerdemain. How did <hi>Harold</hi> carry it? <hi>Malmsbury</hi> tells us by force and violence. What <hi>reaſon of State,</hi> or <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> could make the <hi>Saxons</hi> ſet aſide the next Heir, (if they could have had him for their King) and place in the Throne a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Son of a Conqueror, with his Fathers Army at his Heels? Had not the <hi>Danes</hi> the greateſt ſhare in making him King? and could the <hi>Saxons</hi> think o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, than that they would have the greateſt ſhare in the Government? What Affairs of the Kingdom was <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald</hi> beſt able to manage? Certainly not the Affairs, and <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Saxons:</hi> They could not believe it, when he had an Army, and great numbers of his own Countrymen, with their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, to provide for; and when they could not but ſee, the Nation was to be planted by Foreigners, who muſt be their Maſters. Therefore what <hi>reaſon of State,</hi> what <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> could there be, for <hi>Harolds</hi> carrying of the Crown and Kingdom, as the Author neatly Phraſeth it?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Words of the Author, <hi>p.</hi> 18.</head>
               <p>For if there be no Rule, it is not poſſible to ſatisfie <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the Niceties of Titles, If there be a Rule, the <hi>general conſent</hi> of the people, joyned with the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good,</hi> ſeems to have been that which our Anceſtors proceeded by.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be oppoſed to this ſaying.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>general Conſent</hi> of the People, in conjunction with <hi>Common Good,</hi> or theſe two joyned, never was actually in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, nor never can be. Where, or how can all the People meet? or if that could be, how can they joyn in eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Notion of <hi>Common Good?</hi> Were they ever all of one mind? Were not they ever, ſince things were, of divers Parties, and thoſe of different Judgments, what the <hi>Common Good</hi> was? Was there not partiality in every Party? And did not every Party helieve that was the <hi>Common Good,</hi> which they apprehended to be ſo, and ſuited beſt with their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and Propoſals to themſelves? But the People meet by their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. Did ever all the People meet to chooſe them? Hath not a Party com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly choſen for the whole, excluding all others? Or have not Men of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty impoſed themſelves upon the People, and uſurped the general conſent of the whole? Upon a ſtrict enquiry, this will appear to have been the general Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Where then is the <hi>General Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> of the People; as for <hi>Common Good,</hi> enough hath been ſaid before to invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date that pretence; and for the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the General conſent of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Common Good,</hi> the Author talks of, let him ſhew it practicable if he can. <hi>Do as you would be done by,</hi> is the Ground and Foundation of <hi>Common Good</hi> (as hath been ſaid before) but when, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59535:11"/> where did the general and free Conſent of the People, high and low, concur and unite in this Foundation? If all Men would build upon it, none could receive wrong or injury; there could be no Diſputes about any matter whatever, if Men would make this Rule the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Actions. In the mean time, while Men can arrive at this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, The <hi>Legal Conſtitution</hi> by which the Kingdom hath flouriſht, and been ſupported in great Reputation for ſome hundreds of years, is the beſt and ſafeſt Rule for all <hi>ſober Men</hi> (to uſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Phraſe) to proceed by. When Men go from the Law, and legal Eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment, they walk in the dark, and go they know not whither, and travel while they make themſelves not only uneaſie but miſerable.</p>
                  <p>'Tis a ſtrange fate upon the People, that their name is always uſed; their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit pretended; their power to create right to Govern, and Governors magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by reſtleſs Projectors, whoſe only deſign is to dig up the very Foundations of <hi>Legal Settlements,</hi> and ſuch as by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages have been found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to have been for the eaſe, quiet, and benefit of the People, who are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in greater danger, than when they liſten to ſuch Men, that promiſe to make them happy by <hi>Eutopian,</hi> Illegal, and Impracticable Schemes and Devices; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſery and deſolation is brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, their Conſent is pretended, and vouched to warrant it. If the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor could have prevailed with himſelf to have read the ſeveral Declarations, Remonſtrances, and almoſt innumerable other Papers, printed between the years 1640. and 1660. all filled with the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Rights,</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> and holding forth <hi>Common Good,</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt,</hi> and aſſerting and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both thoſe <hi>impracticable</hi> Notions (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch manner, as the People are made to believe they belong unto them) in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry change of Affairs and Government, that then happened; he could not have been ſo fond of, or ſo often have vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to no purpoſe repeated theſe two empty, idle ſayings, and expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 19.</head>
               <p>I take ours to be a true, <hi>original Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy;</hi> eſpecially after the Rights of the leſſer Monarchies were ſwallowed up, or deliver'd into that of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings. And farther, I do not ſtick to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that it was <hi>Hereditary,</hi> where the <hi>Right of Succeſſion</hi> and the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> did not interfere, <hi>i. e.</hi> where there was not a <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>moral</hi> Incapacity; a <hi>natural,</hi> as in the Sons of the Elder <hi>Edmond,</hi> when <hi>Edred</hi> was made King before them; a Moral, as when <hi>Edgar</hi>'s Elder Brother was ſet aſide for ill Government by one half of the Nation, and the other never diſputed the matter with them.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be ſaid this.</head>
                  <p>As to his Diſtinction of <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Incapacity,</hi> ſince a Protector, or a Protector and Council may ſupply, and have often ſupplied both thoſe incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, it ſignifies nothing. And as to his Examples of <hi>Edred</hi>'s Government in the Minority of <hi>Edmunds</hi> Sons; and of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wy, Edgar</hi>'s elder Brother, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by half the Nation, they have been ſpoken to before.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's words in the ſame Page.</head>
               <p>Theſe things I mention to ſhew, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this were a <hi>true and ſucceſſive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> in ordinary courſe; yet where the <hi>Publick Good</hi> was by the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Realm judged to require it; they thought it no <hi>Perjury</hi> or <hi>breach of Faith,</hi> to transfer their Allegiance, although it were without the conſent of the actual Governor, or the next Lineal Heir.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59535:11"/>
                  <head>What may be ſaid to this Paſſage.</head>
                  <p>The things hitherto mentioned by the Author, were his <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; and whatever appears by thoſe Inſtances to have been done, was done by a <hi>Party</hi> (as hath been ſhewn from undoubted Hiſtory) and not by <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> yet ſuch <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> or <hi>Parties</hi> he calls the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Realm,</hi> as his Tutor <hi>Robert Parſons</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> alias <hi>Doleman,</hi> hath taught him; eſpecially in the 4th, 7th, 8th, and 9th Chapters of the firſt part of his <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about the Succeſſion to the Crown of England:</hi> where are to be found all the Author's <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Inſtances ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and applied in the ſame manner, and to the ſame purpoſe, as they are in this Author; and alſo his two <hi>Norman Inſtances,</hi> that of <hi>Maud</hi> the <hi>Empreſs, Hen.</hi> 2, and King <hi>Stephen;</hi> the other of the two Houſes of <hi>Tork</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> in his Second Part of the <hi>Conference,</hi> cap. 2. and 3. and likewiſe in Mr. <hi>Pryns firſt Part of the Sovereignty of Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> p. 7, 8, 9. and the two <hi>Norman</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances p. 94, 95. Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> followed <hi>Dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who ſays <hi>all Kings that take Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oaths are Elected.</hi> Conf. <hi>of</hi> Succeſs: part 1. cap. 5. and <hi>all Invaders, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders, that ſet up themſelves by the help of a Party only, were Elected and ſet up by the States, or Commonwealth.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Parties</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> calls the <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> calls <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the very ſame Inſtances; but this Author is beſt pleaſed with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Expreſſions, and uſeth them moſt frequently. But if he had conſider'd what Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> hath written ſince the year 1648. and in that year againſt his own former Notions and Opinions, about the <hi>Sovereignty of Parliament and Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. eſpecially his <hi>Plea for the Houſe of Lords, his four Parts of a brief Regiſter of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Writs,</hi> his <hi>Animadverſions upon</hi> Coke's 4th. <hi>Inſtitute,</hi> and many other Writings, and the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> to them; He would never have Publiſht ſuch Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, baffled by him, and many others.</p>
                  <p>If the <hi>States</hi> (as he calls them) had had upon the Conſideration of <hi>Publick Good,</hi> the Power he ſpeaks of, and that it was known and legal; or if the Crown had according to the Conſtitution been at their Diſpoſal; ſuppoſing the <hi>Saxon E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> had freely choſen <hi>Canutus,</hi> as he vainly Aſſerts; what could prompt him to cauſe <hi>Edwin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Flor. Wig. A. D. <hi>1016.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Edmond Ironſide</hi>'s Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be murder'd, and to ſend his two Sons <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Edmond</hi> to the King of <hi>Sweves,</hi> that they alſo might be murder'd? And if the Succeſſion had not been notoriouſly, wholly, and complete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hereditary; what need he to have feared the Title, and Succeſſion of the Sons and Brother of <hi>Edmond,</hi> if it had been true what the Author inſinuates, that he was legally Elected, and upon account of the <hi>Publick Good?</hi> Beſides impoſing Parties, ſmall Numbers, and Factions upon his Readers, and calling them the <hi>States;</hi> he hath another pretty knack of impoſing upon them, by telling them <hi>Oaths</hi> made to foreign Kings (ſuch as the <hi>Danes</hi> were) and forced upon the Nation by Foreign Armies) was trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of Allegiance; as if the People then were wonderfully pleaſed, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their new Maſters. From theſe Inſtances and Topicks he might as well have proved, that becauſe this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath been overrun, and poſſeſt by <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> with their miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Aſſiſtants; therefore it may be expedient it ſhould <hi>be ſo again.</hi> They ſeem to be Arguments to encourage ſuch another undertaking, rather than any thing elſe.</p>
                  <p>After the <hi>Saxon</hi> Conſtitution, he comes to the <hi>Norman,</hi> and there makes only two Inſtances.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The words of the Author, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>The firſt Inſtance I ſhall bring, is in the Caſe of the Oath taken to <hi>Maud</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hen. 1.</hi> in the Thirty firſt year of his Reign: and there is no queſtion, but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59535:12"/> ſigned her to ſucceed him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Malmsb.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>noveſt.</hi> l. 1. p. 100. 105. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>legitima &amp; perenni ſucceſſione,</hi> as <hi>Malmsbury</hi>'s words are: but <hi>Stephen</hi> who had before ſworn Allegiance to her) watched his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and by the help of a Party made by his Brother (the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>) he was Crowned <hi>King;</hi> and although at firſt, <hi>Malmsbury</hi> ſaith, <hi>but three Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>very few Noblemen joyned with him;</hi> yet he ſoon after ſaith, <hi>that moſt of them went into him;</hi> and even <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt's natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Son, took an Oath to him, but with the Condition of his preſerving his Honour and Covenants. There are ſeveral things worth our obſervation, in this affair, with reſpect to the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Malmsb.</hi> f. 99. <hi>a. n.</hi> 30.</note>
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 27. <hi>Regni ſui Rex Henricus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliam venit menſe Septembri, adducens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum filiiam ſuam,</hi> &amp;c. In the 27th. year of his Reign King <hi>Henry</hi> came to <hi>England,</hi> in the Month of <hi>September,</hi> and brought with him his Daughter. He called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> a great number of the Clergy and chief Men of the Kingdom at <hi>London;</hi> and being much grieved he was like to have no Children by his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wife, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; he was very thoughtful about a Succeſſor; and having a long time before deliberated about that matter, <hi>Tunc in eodem Concilio, omnes totius Angliae Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, Epiſcopos etiam &amp; Abbate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento adegit &amp; obſtrinxit; ut ſi ipſi ſine haerede maſculo decederet, Matildam filiam ſuam, quondam Imperatricem, incunctanter &amp; ſine ulla retractatione Dominam recipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> Then in the ſame Council he bound all the chief men of <hi>England,</hi> the Biſhops alſo, and Abbats by Oath, that if he ſhould die without Heir Male, they ſhould forthwith, without retraction or revok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Oath, receive his Daughter <hi>Maud,</hi> late <hi>Empreſs,</hi> for their Queen. Having before told them what a great loſs the Nation ſuſtein'd by the death of his Son <hi>William,</hi> to whom <hi>by right</hi> the Kingdom belonged; and now that his Daughter ſurvived, to whom only the <hi>lawful Succeſſion was due,</hi> from her Grandfather, Uncle, and Father, that were Kings, and from the Stock of her Mother many Ages;<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>cui ſoli legitima debeatur ſucceſſio, ab avo, avunculo, &amp; patre regibus, &amp; a materno genere multis retro ſeculis; ſiquidem ab Egbirtho Weſt-Saxonum rege,</hi> &amp;c. For from <hi>Egbert,</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> who firſt ſubdued the other <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings, in the year 800, during the Reign of<note n="*" place="margin">The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian doth not reckon the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, there were 14 <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide them. <hi>Ibid. n.</hi> 50. <hi>b.</hi> lin. 1. &amp;c. <hi>Ibid. f.</hi> 100. <hi>a. n.</hi> 40.</note> Fourteen Kings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the year 1043. when <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> was Crowned King, <hi>the Line of the Royal Blood never failed, nor was there one wrong ſtep, or halt made in the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; nec unquam ejuſdem regalis ſanguinis linea defecit, nec in Succeſſione regni clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicavit.</hi> All Perſons of any moment in this Council did take the Oath, firſt <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> then the other Biſhops and Abbats. The firſt of the Lay-men that took it, was <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scors,</hi> the next <hi>Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Mortaign,</hi> and <hi>Bologn</hi> (afterward King <hi>Stephen</hi>) and then <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi>'s natural Son.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno.</hi> 31. <hi>Regni ſui Rex Henricus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diit in Angliam,</hi> &amp;c. In the thirtyfirſt year of his Reign, King <hi>Henry</hi> returned into <hi>England,</hi> and the Empreſs alſo; and in a great Aſſembly of the Nobility or Great Men at <hi>Northampton,</hi> thoſe which had ſworn before, renewed their Oath, and thoſe that had not, did then ſwear, or give their Faith unto her.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> died in the Thirty fifth year of his Reign;<note place="margin">Ibid. b. n. <hi>30.</hi>
                     </note> and in his Sickneſs being asked by <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and the Nobleman that were then with him, about a Succeſſor; <hi>a quibus de ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſore interrogatus, filiae omnem terram ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, citra &amp; ultra mare, legitima &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renni Succeſſione adjudicavit,</hi> he gave all his Lands every where to his Daughter, as to his Lawful Succeſſor.</p>
                  <p>After the death of King <hi>Henry,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. f. <hi>101.</hi> a. lin. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> which happen'd upon the firſt of <hi>December</hi> that year; the <hi>Empreſs, Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> with moſt of the Noblemen, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd their return for <hi>England:</hi> whereas
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59535:12"/> 
                     <hi>Stephen</hi> made all the haſte he could, and by the readieſt Paſſage being come, the <hi>Londoners</hi> and People of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> own him a King:<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> And he drew unto him <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>William de Pont Larch,</hi> Keeper of the King's Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: But all his Endeavars had come to nothing,<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> if his Brother <hi>Henry</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and at that time the <hi>Pope's Legat,</hi> had not been his beſt Aſſiſtant. <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> required of him an Oath, That he would reſtore and preſerve the Liberties of the Church, and the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> became his Surety<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the doing of it. He was very ſweet in his Promiſes, but they wanted performance. He was Crowned the 22 of <hi>December,</hi> there being preſent only three Biſhops, the Archbiſhop, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and <hi>Salisbury,</hi> no Abbats, and but few Noble or Great Men.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>Coronatus eſt ergo in regem Angliae Stephanus, undeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o Calend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Januarii</hi> 1135. <hi>tribus Epiſcopis praſentibus, Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo, Wintonienſi, Saresberienſi, null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, panciſſimus Optimatibus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note>Having made the Treaſurers of his Party, he immediately became Maſter of the Treaſure, which was near 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in ready Money, beſides Gold and Silver Veſſels of great weight, and ineſtimable value. Having ſo great Treaſure, he could not want Aſſiſtants,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>hanc copi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m Gazarum habenti, auxiliatores d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſſe non poterant,</hi> eſpecially being very profuſe in his Gifts. All ſorts of Soldiers ſtock'd to him out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Britany,</hi> moſt notorious Plunderers,<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>50.</hi>
                     </note> and cruel People, who robbed Churches, and pulled Men of Religious. Orders from their Horſes, and impriſoned them, without regard, <hi>Erat genus hominum rapaciſſimum &amp; violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum, qui nil penſi haberent vel caeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria frangere, vel Eccleſias expilare, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſi quinetiam ordinis viros non ſolùm e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis proturbare, ſed etiam indigenae militer, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Neither were Strangers only, but home-bred Soldiers or Knights, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Times of Peace, toward the end of King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Reign, becauſe then they lived meanly, eaſily brought to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, raiſing thereby their Fortunes from the Loſs and Ruin of the People,<note place="margin">Ibid. b. lin. <hi>2.</hi> Ibid. lin. <hi>3, 4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineialium diſpendio ſuas fortunas urgentes;</hi> Further, <hi>Stephen</hi> when he was <hi>Earl,</hi> by his eaſie and jocular Converſation, and his Familiarity with ther meaneſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, had wonderfully gain'd the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the People,<note place="margin">Ibid. lin. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> ſo that all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen of <hi>England</hi> came readily in to him. In the mean time, the wiſe <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> was folic ous how he might ſhew them their Faults, and by Diſcourſe bring them back to a better Opinion; for there was nothing to be attempted by Force,<note place="margin">Ibid. lin. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> for the Cauſes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; nor was it free for him to come into <hi>England,</hi> unleſs for a time he could diſſemble, and appear as if he were a Party in the Defection, <hi>(quaſi defectionis eorum particeps)</hi> wherefore he did Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the King upon Condition,<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> that is to ſay, ſo long as he kept his Dignity entire, and performed his Agreement and Covenants, <hi>ſcilicet quamdiu ille digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſuam integre cuſtodiret, &amp; ſibi pacta ſervaret:</hi> For long before he knew the Temper of the King, and foreſaw the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtability of his Faith, <hi>ſpectato enim jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dudum regis ingenio, inſtabilitatem fidei praevidebat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame Year,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> not much after the coming of the <hi>Earl,</hi> the Biſhops ſware Fealty to the King, ſo long as he ſhould preſerve the Liberty, and ſtrict Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. n.</hi> 20. 30.</note> which he then ſwore to do according to his Charter, that conſiſts moſtly of Privileges grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Clergy, and is there repeated, and is dated 1136, in the firſt Year of his Reign. But the Hiſtorian ſays, He diſdain'd to put the Names of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which were many, becauſe he changed all things ſo perverſly, as if he had only ſworn, that he might ſhew the whole Kingdom, he had ſworn to what he never intended to perform;<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>nomina Teſtium, qui multi fuêrunt, apponere faſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio; quia pene omnia ita perperam mutâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, quaſi ad hoc tantum jurâſſet, ut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicatorem ſacramenti ſe regno toti oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret.</hi> In this Grant, he ſays, he was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59535:13"/> choſen King by the Clergy and Laity, crowned by <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and afterwards confirmed by <hi>Pope Innoeent;</hi> the <hi>Bull</hi> of which <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> may be ſeen in the Hiſtory of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Prior of Hagulſtad,</hi> col. 313. n 30. The Witneſſes to his Charter, or Grant, were moſt of the Biſhops, Earls, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, and all <hi>Normans,</hi> and may be found in the ſame Hiſtory, <hi>Col.</hi> 314. <hi>n</hi> 60. This is the true Hiſtory, how <hi>Stephen</hi> came to be King, taken from <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> who lived and wrote at the very time theſe things were done, and wrote them at the Requeſt of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>The firſt Obſervation upon his own Hiſtory of <hi>Maud</hi>'s Title, and <hi>Stephen</hi>'s coming to the Crown before noted, is, That if it hold that an Oath was firſt taken to <hi>Maud</hi> by the Biſhops and Nobility, and afterwards to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> an Oath of Allegiance may ceaſe without Diſcharge from the Party to whom it was made; and ſo the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Biſhops of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> and <hi>Salisbury,</hi> as well as the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> thought themſelves at liberty to take a new Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> without a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe</hi> from the Party concerned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oath.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be ſaid to this.</head>
                  <p>'Tis not to be doubted, but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor knows <hi>what Religion</hi> was profeſt in this Nation at that time, and only that; and knows alſo, thoſe of that Perſuaſion did, and do believe the Head of their Church had, and hath Power to make an Oath ceaſe, without diſcharge from the Party to whom it is made: And ſo the three Biſhops thought themſelves at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to take a new Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> without a Releaſe from the Party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the former Oath, when they had his Authority; and that they ſo had, is manifeſt from the following brief Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative. <hi>Stephen</hi> was crowned on the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of the <hi>Kalends</hi> of <hi>January,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. f. <hi>101.</hi> a. n. <hi>20.</hi> Ibid. n. <hi>40.</hi> Ibid. b. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> or 22 of <hi>December;</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> after <hi>Eaſter</hi> next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; and it was after his coming, that the Biſhops ſware Fealty to <hi>Stephen, Eodem anno non multùm poſt adventum Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis juravêrunt Epiſcopi Fidelitatem regi, &amp;c.</hi> at which time he alſo ſwore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Liberty, and ſtrict Diſcipline of the Church, as they were drawn up in a Charter or Grant, in which the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Confirmation of his Title is mentioned; the beginning whereof runs thus: <hi>Ego Stephanus Dei gratiâ,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>aſſenſu Cleri &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli in Regem Angliae electus, &amp; a Domino Wilielmo Archiepiſcopo Cantuariae, &amp; Sanctae Eccleſim Romanae Legato conſecratus, &amp; ab Innocentio Sanctae ſedis Romanae Pontifice poſtmodum confirmatus, &amp;c.</hi> I <hi>Stephen</hi> by the Grace of God, by the Aſſent of the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>People</hi> choſen King of <hi>England,</hi> crowned by <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and the <hi>Legat</hi> of the <hi>Roman See, (who was his Brother)</hi> and confirmed by <hi>Pope Innocent, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And notwithſtanding he was at firſt ſet up by the Fraud and Artifice of three or four Perſons, and the Biſhops eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, who <hi>then govern'd</hi> the Nation, and that he immediately <hi>forced</hi> himſelf upon the then <hi>Norman Government</hi> by an Army of <hi>Foreigners, plundring</hi> and <hi>cruel Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings,</hi> and <hi>Britans,</hi> and <hi>home-bred Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Soldiers,</hi> that knew not how to live, as appears by the Hiſtory before-recited; yet the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſuggeſted to to the <hi>Pope,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Richard</hi> Prior of <hi>Haguſtald</hi> or <hi>Hexti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Col.</hi> 313. n. 30, 40, &amp;c. in the Body of the Bull.</note> That after the Death of King <hi>Henry, Religion</hi> in <hi>England</hi> was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, <hi>turbata eſt religio in regno Angliae, &amp; nullum mandatum pacis ſeu juſtitia in adjutorio regali vigebat,</hi> and there was no Royal Command for either Peace or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: and that the greateſt Wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were committed with impunity, <hi>atque atrocitatem tantorum ſcelerum comitabatur impunitas,</hi> and that for the putting a ſtop to ſuch Evils, <hi>Stephen</hi> was <hi>choſen</hi> King <hi>communi voto, &amp; unanimi aſſenſu tam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerum, quam etiam populi,</hi> by the common Vote and unanimous Aſſent of the Great Men and People, and crowned by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59535:13"/> Biſhops; and all this was teſtified by the <hi>Letters</hi> or <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and Biſhops of the Countrey, and the Lovers of the Holy <hi>Romane Church,</hi> the glorious King of <hi>France,</hi> and illuſtrious Earl<note n="†" place="margin">This was <hi>Theobald,</hi> Earl of <hi>Blois, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi>'s el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
                     <hi>Theobald; Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum venerabilium fratrum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Archiepiſcoporum earundem Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. &amp; Amatorum Sanctae Romanae Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, glorieſi Francorum Regis, &amp; illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrius Viri Comitis Theobaldi ſcripta te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantur.</hi> Then upon this recounting the Suggeſtions, the Pope and Title-Maker, ſays, <hi>Nos cognoſcentes Vota tantorum Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum, in perſonam tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m praecunte di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina Gratia conveniſſe, &amp;c.</hi> We know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Votes of ſuch great Men to have concurr'd in the Choice of thy Perſon, by the Guidance of Divine Grace. And for theſe things, and his promiſe of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and doing Honour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he confirms wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t had been done, and grants him the ſame Honour and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative he had granted to his Predeceſſor <hi>Henry.</hi> This <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Confirmation</hi> was directed to King <hi>Stephen; Innocentius Epiſcopus, &amp;c. cariſſimo in Chriſto filio Stephano illuſtri Anglorum regi ſalutem &amp; Apoſtolicam benedictionem.</hi> From the precedent Narrative it is evident the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſollicited this <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and obtained it before they ſware Fealty to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> though upon falſe Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions: However, the <hi>Pope</hi> knew he was choſen by the Guidance of Divine Grace, and the Biſhops and Nobility be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved him to be infallible; or, at leaſt, had ſuch a D ference to his Confirmation of <hi>Stephen,</hi> that they took themſelves to be diſcharged and releaſed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om their Oaths made to <hi>Maud;</hi> for if this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation was valid, her Title was made null and void.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>msb. f. <hi>108.</hi> a.n. <hi>40, 50.</hi>
                     </note>That ſuch as favour'd <hi>Stephen,</hi> own'd his Title from the <hi>Pope,</hi> it is evident from his Brother the <hi>Legat</hi>'s Speech (who left <hi>Stephen,</hi> and adhered to <hi>Maud;</hi> and then revolted from her, to him again,) when he called a Council at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by his Legantine Power, wherein chiding Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the <hi>Pope</hi> were read, becauſe he had not delivered his Brother <hi>Stephen,</hi> then in Priſon; in which he was exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to do it, either by Eccleſiaſtical or Secular Power: After the reading where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he made a Speech in excuſe of his faithleſs Actions, and commanded thoſe preſent, on b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf of God and the Pope, <hi>(ex parte Dei &amp; Apoſtolici)</hi> that they ſhould aid the King with their utmoſt Power, who was anointed by the Will of the People, and Aſſent of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick See, <hi>(voluntate populi, &amp; aſſenſu Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtolicae ſedis inunctum)</hi> and to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate all Perturbers of the Peace, <hi>that favoured the Dutcheſs of</hi> Anjou, <hi>i. e. Maud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Author had underſtood this, he would ſcarcely have ventured upon this Inſtance, to have confirmed his Opinion about the Releaſe and Diſcharging of Oaths.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Words of the Author, <hi>p.</hi> 23.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That upon the Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> II. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> her ſelf was ſet aſide, and <hi>Stephen</hi> was to continue King for his Life, and <hi>Henry</hi> II. to ſucceed him. Now, if Oaths of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> muſt not be interperted by the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good,</hi> here are inſuperable Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as to the Obligations of theſe Oaths, for the <hi>Allegiance</hi> was transferred from the right Heir, to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper; as <hi>Stephen</hi> muſt be owned to have been by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe who deny that <hi>Allegiance</hi> can be transferred from the right Heir: And they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper for his Life, which is repugnant to the nature of our Conſtitution, if it be founded <hi>in a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Legal Succeſſion.</hi> And again, <hi>Maud,</hi> to whom they had ſworn, is ſet aſide, and the Reverſion of the Crown it entailed on her Son, although ſhe was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>What may be replied to this.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>inſuperable Difficulties</hi> have been overcome before in the Diſcourſe about the Pope's Confirmation of King <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen:</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59535:14"/> As to <hi>Maud</hi>'s having been ſet aſide, it ſhall be conſidered in the laſt Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph of this Inſtance, and alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſaid of this <hi>Publick Good,</hi> which brought on this Agreement, and what it was; but it muſt needs be ſo, becauſe done by the Common-Council of the Nation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's Words in the ſame Page.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1153. <hi>Paris,</hi> ibid.</note>
                  <hi>Matt. Weſtm.</hi> and <hi>Paris</hi> ſay, The Right of King <hi>Henry</hi> II. was declared by King <hi>Stephen, in conventu Epiſcoporum, &amp; aliorum de regno Optimatum;</hi> which was the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcription of a <hi>Parliament</hi> at that time, for as yet the <hi>Baronage repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> the Nation; which ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ws how far the <hi>publick Good</hi> was thought to be the Meaſure of the Obligation of theſe Oaths. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Newburge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſis</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>num publicum</hi> was the Foundation of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1153.</note> And <hi>M. Weſtminſter,</hi> that the King and Lords did all ſwear to it, and a ſolemn Charter was made of it, and k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt in a moſt ſecure place.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>HISTORY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">M.W ſtm. A. D. <hi>1153</hi> f. <hi>246.</hi> n. <hi>10</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Diligentia Theobaldi Archiepiſcopi Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuartenſi, &amp; Epiſcoporum r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gni Rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum Stephanus, &amp; D x N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mannorum H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nricus, apud Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ingford talem concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam inierunt, &amp;c.</hi> By the D ligence of <hi>Theobald</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Biſhops of the Kingdom the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Agreement was made between King <hi>Stephen,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> at <hi>Walingford.</hi> King <hi>Stephen</hi> not having an Heir, except only Duke <hi>Henry,</hi> did acknowledge, in an Aſſembly of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other chief Men of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that Duke <hi>Henry</hi> had the heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Right to the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> and the Duke kindly granted, that King <hi>Stephen</hi> ſhould, during his Life, peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly enjoy <hi>his</hi> Kingdom. The Agreement was ſo co firmed, that the King him elf, and the Biſhops then preſent, with the reſt of the beſt Men of the Kingdom, ſware that Duke <hi>Henry,</hi> after the Death of the King, if he ſhould outlive him, ſhould enjoy the Kingdom, without all Contradiction: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which Agreement there was a Charter made, which was kept in a moſt ſecure place.<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is what the Hiſtorian hath, in both places, cited by the Author. The whole Charter is in <hi>Brompton,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Brompton, col. <hi>1037.</hi> n. <hi>60.</hi>
                     </note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus: <hi>Stephanus R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x Angliae, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, Abbatibus, Comiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Juſtitiariis, Vicecomitibus, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>roni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; omnibus fidelibus, ſuis ſalutem: Sciatis, quod Ego Rex Stephanus Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Ducem Norman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ae poſt me Succeſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem regni Angliae, &amp; hae edem meum j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re haereditario conſtitus, &amp; ſic e: &amp; haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis regnum Ang iae donavi &amp; conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavi: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x vero propter hunc honorem, &amp; Donationem &amp; Confirmationem, ſibi a me factam, Homagio michi &amp; Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſecuritatem fecit, ſcilicet q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chi erit. &amp; vitam &amp; hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rem meum pro ſuo poſſe cuſtodiet, per Conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones inter nos praeloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tas quae in hac Charta continentur. Stephen,</hi> K ng of <hi>England, &amp;c</hi> Know ye, that I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> after me, and my Heir by hereditary Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and ſo have given and confirmed the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to him and his Heirs: For which Honour, Donation and Confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mation made by me to him, he gave me Security by Homage and Oath, that he would be faithful to me, and preſerve my Life and Honour to the utmoſt of his power, according to the Agreements made by us, which are contained in this Charter. <hi>Neubrigenſis</hi> ſpeaking of this Treaty, ſays,<note place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>30.</hi> p. <hi>104.</hi> In Paris, Ed. <hi>1610.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t inter eos</hi> (that is, the King and Duke) <hi>ſolemne &amp; ſalubre colleq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ium celebrari, ubi amicis mediantibus, &amp; circa bonum publicum pia &amp; prudenti proviſione ſata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x inter eos &amp; caute formata, &amp; ſolide firmata eſt.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey agreed to have a ſolemn and wholſome Treaty, where, by the Mediation of Friends, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a pious and prudent reſpect to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59535:14"/> common Good,</hi> a Peace was warily made, and ſolidly confirmed.<note place="margin">Ibidem, p. <hi>105.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Quibus Deo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitio ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>briter actis, Rex Angliam, &amp; Anglia pacem recepit: annis enim jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plurimis, fere nudo regis nomine inſignis, tunc recipere viſus eſt hujus rem nominis; &amp; quaſi tunc primo regnare coepit, quia tunc primo purgata Invaſionis, Tyrannica macula, legitimi principis juſtitiam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit.</hi> Which things being done by God's Aſſiſtance, the King received <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> received Peace; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the bare name of King for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years, now he enjoyed the thing it ſelf, and began then firſt to reign becauſe then the Blot of Tyrannical Invaſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt wiped out, he exerciſed the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of a lawful King.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Author's further Words about this Accord, <hi>p.</hi> 22.</head>
               <p>And thus the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> were continued to one that had no Right, for his Life; and made to one who predended to no R ght, but after his Mother, who was ſet aſide in this Agreement; for we never read that ſhe was preſent at the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or reſigned her Right to the Crown. So that here were three Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance at once; that to <hi>Maud</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, that to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> and to <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> II. and yet the <hi>general Good</hi> of the Nation muſt give an <hi>equitable Senſe</hi> of theſe Oaths, or there muſt be <hi>Perjury</hi> on all ſides.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Anſwer to what the Author ſays, about this Agreement, and the Excluſion of <hi>Maud, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>By this Accord it was owned by King <hi>Stephen,</hi> Biſhops and Barons, which were then the Parliament, or <hi>Colloquium,</hi> as the Author confeſſeth, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Right was in Duke <hi>Henry,</hi> and he granted that King <hi>Stephen,</hi> during his Life, ſhould peaceably enjoy his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And if the Right was in <hi>Henry,</hi> might he not recede from it if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? And the Agreement ſays, he did during <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Life. This Retroceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made the Biſhops and Barons Oaths to the Agreement lawful; and if he had not ſome teſtimony of a Ceſſion, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, by and from his Mother, though not mentioned in the Agreement, this Convention could not, upon <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Acknowledgment only, have own'd his hereditary Right upon Oath. And that by Ceſſion, or ſome other way, ſhe did quit and leave her Right to govern, to her Son, 'tis moſt probable, from what follows. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd</hi> the Empreſs,<note place="margin">Malm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. f. <hi>104.</hi> a.n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> upon the death of her Father, and the Invaſion of <hi>Stephen,</hi> on the 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h of <hi>September,</hi> in the Year 1139, came into <hi>England</hi> with her Brother <hi>Robert,</hi> and managed the War againſt him in her own Perſon, her Son being but a Child,<note place="margin">He was born, <hi>A.D.</hi> 1133.</note> and her Husband engaged in the Defence of <hi>Normandy, Anjon, &amp;c.</hi> againſt the King of <hi>France.</hi> Her three great Supports were, her half Brother <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulph</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and <hi>Milo</hi> Earl of <hi>Hereford;</hi> the laſt,<note place="margin">Chaon. Gervas. Col. <hi>1359.</hi> n. <hi>10,</hi> Col. <hi>1361.</hi> n. <hi>10.</hi> Col. <hi>1362.</hi> n. <hi>10.</hi> lin. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> to her very great Grief, died in the Year 1143. the ſecond made his Peace with King <hi>Stephen,</hi> 1145. and the firſt, <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> died in the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> in the Year 1146. of an high Fever, after he had ſent <hi>Henry,</hi> then being about thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years of Age, over to his Father, into <hi>Normandy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After the loſs of theſe Friends and Supports, the Empreſs,<note place="margin">Ibidem, Col. <hi>1363.</hi> lin. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> wearied out with theſe Commotions and Wars in <hi>England,</hi> before <hi>Lent,</hi> in the Year 1147. paſſed over into <hi>Normandy,</hi> chuſing rather to live there with her Husband in Peace, than undergo ſo many Troubles.</p>
                  <p>In the Year 1149.<note place="margin">Ibidem, Col. <hi>1366.</hi> n. <hi>30.</hi> Col. <hi>1367.</hi> n <hi>30.</hi> Chr. Norm. f. <hi>984</hi> B.C. A.D <hi>1150</hi> M W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtin. eod. An.</note> 
                     <hi>Henry</hi> came into <hi>England</hi> with an Army, in the Month of <hi>May;</hi> and returned into <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mandy</hi> in the beginning of <hi>January</hi> next following, without Succeſs.</p>
                  <p>In the Year 1150. <hi>Henry</hi> took poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Mother's Inheritance, <hi>(haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatem matris,)</hi> the Dukedom of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy,</hi> and did Homage to <hi>Lew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> King
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59535:15"/> of <hi>France,</hi> for it; his Father <hi>Geofrey</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent both when he took Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and did Homage; and they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together from <hi>Paris</hi> rejoicing; and no doubt, if they two were ſo well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with what had been done, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could not be diſſatisfied, nor could it be done without her Conſent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem, D. A. D. <hi>1150</hi>
                     </note>On the 7th of <hi>September</hi> his Father <hi>Geofrey</hi> died, and gave to <hi>Henry</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> his eldeſt Son, the Earldom of <hi>Anjou. Henrico Duci Normanniae, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenito ſuo conceſſit Comitatam Andega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chr. Gerv. Col.</hi> 1372. <hi>n.</hi> 30. The old Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar at <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
                     </note>In the Year 1153. Duke <hi>Henry,</hi> all things being quiet beyond Sea, came with ſome Forces into <hi>England,</hi> on the 1ſt of <hi>January:</hi> His C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ming was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner known, but the Earls and great Men flocked to him; and upon the 8th of the ſame Month, the Year following, the Agreement was made between King <hi>S ephen</hi> and Duke <hi>Henry. Matth. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> ſays it was made <hi>A. D.</hi> 1153.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chr. Norm. f <hi>1101.</hi> D A. D. <hi>1166</hi>
                     </note>From the time <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſs left <hi>England,</hi> in the Year 1147 ſhe is not ſo much as mentioned by any Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, until the time of her death, which was on the 4th of the Ides, or 10th of <hi>September,</hi> 1166.</p>
                  <p>From theſe Particulars 'tis moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if not certain, that ſhe was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with, and conſented to this Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either at the time it was made, or by Ceſſion from the Kingdom and Government, by relinquiſhing it, and leaving the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Management to her Son, who was now Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> Earl of <hi>Anjou,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. f. <hi>985.</hi> C.</note> and, in Right of his Wife <hi>Alienor,</hi> Duke of <hi>Aquitain;</hi> and being now above twenty Years of Age, fit for Action. When he came for <hi>England,</hi> ſhe was in her declining Age, her Years being then about fifty; and fixing her Mind upon Works of Charity, ſhe ſpent the reſt of her Days in performing of them;<note place="margin">Ib. f. <hi>1101.</hi> D.</note> for ſhe built three Monaſteries in <hi>Normandy;</hi> one of <hi>Ciſterſians,</hi> in the Country of <hi>Caux;</hi> another of <hi>Canons,</hi> near <hi>Cherburgh;</hi> and a third of <hi>Canons,</hi> in the Foreſt of <hi>Goſer;</hi> and for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Stone B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idge of <hi>Rhoven,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the River <hi>Seyn,</hi> which had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by her, ſhe gave a great Summ of Money. She was a Woman of a very brisk and high Spirit, as appears by her Actions in <hi>England;</hi> and after ſhe left it, ſhe lived nineteen Years, and twelve or thirteen after her Son was King: So as, if ſhe had not relinquiſhed her Right to <hi>England,</hi> as ſhe had done about three Years before this Agreement, to <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> the Hiſtorians could not have been ſo ſilent concerning her.</p>
                  <p>So that from hence 'tis evident, that ſuch as had taken the three Oaths were ſafe; for, upon <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d's</hi> Ceſſion, or relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing her Right, the Obligation of the Oath made to her ceaſed. Then the Oath made to <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſeeing it was done by the Conſent of <hi>Henry,</hi> who had the Right, became lawful. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e can be no Scruple about the Legality of the Oath made to <hi>H nry,</hi> who, upon the Ceſſion of his Mother, had the hereditary Right; and this is ſuggeſted and owned in the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>But the Author ſays, <hi>The general Good of the Nation muſt give an equitable Senſe of theſe Oaths, or there muſt be Perjury on all ſides.</hi> What could this <hi>general Good</hi> then be? It could not be the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> in a <hi>true</hi> ſenſe, for the Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k and Body of the People were <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Saxons;</hi> (for though the <hi>Normans</hi> had taken away their Eſtates, and made them Slaves, as appears by <hi>Dooms-day-Book,</hi> and the black Book in the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> yet we read not that they maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred or murthered them.) And what <hi>general Good</hi> did they receive by, or what <hi>equitable Senſe</hi> did, or could, what was <hi>general Good</hi> to them, give to the <hi>Normans</hi> Oaths? For all the Biſhops and Noblemen that took theſe Oaths, were <hi>Normans:</hi> All the Biſhops, Earls and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, that were Witneſſes to the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Agreement, and ſware to it, in number thirty ſeven, were <hi>Normans,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:59535:15"/> except <hi>Geofrey</hi> of <hi>Monmuth,</hi> a <hi>Welſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or <hi>Britain,</hi> then Biſhop of St. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaph.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">That <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was an Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Strangers, (meaning the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi>) and governed by Foreig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Malmſ. f.</hi> 52. <hi>a. n.</hi> 40.</note> 
                     <hi>Malm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bury</hi> wrote at this time, and ſays, when he wrote, there was no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Engliſhman</hi> a Duke; that is, a great, or leading Man, a Biſhop, or an Abbot; all ſorts of Outlandiſh-men devoured the Riches and Bowels of <hi>England,</hi> nor was there any hopes this Miſery would have an end. <hi>Anglia facta eſt exterorum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatio, &amp; alieniginarum dominatio; nullus hodie Anglus, vel Dux, vel Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex, vel Abbas. Advenae quique divitias &amp; viſcera corrodunt Angliae, nec ulla ſpes finiendae miſeriae.</hi> And in another place, ſpeaking of the Battle of <hi>Haſtings,</hi> he ſays,<note place="margin">Ibid. f <hi>57.</hi> a. n. <hi>30.</hi>
                     </note> That was the fatal Day to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> the lamentable Deſtruction of his ſweet Country, by its receiving new Lords and Maſters. <hi>Illa fuit dies fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Anglis, funeſtum excidium dulcis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae pro novorum Dominorum commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the Author tell the World, how the <hi>general Good</hi> of a Nation that were miſerable People, and Slaves, could give an <hi>equitable Senſe</hi> of their Conquerors, and cruel domineering Maſters Oaths. Let him ſhew how the <hi>general Good</hi> of any Nation can give an <hi>equitable Senſe</hi> to the Oaths of ſuch Men who were edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in Perjury, Rapine, Murther, and and all ſorts of Barbarities and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; whoſe Gain and Advantage was the Meaſure of all their Actions. In the Year 1104, or 1105, notwithſtanding all the great <hi>Normans</hi> had ſwore Fealty to their true and lawful Duke <hi>Robert,</hi> yet when <hi>Henry</hi> came from <hi>England</hi> with good ſtore of Money, they ran after him, and delivered to him Caſtles and fortified Towns.<note place="margin">Eadmer. f. <hi>80.</hi> lin. <hi>1.</hi> A D. <hi>1104.</hi> Hoved. f. <hi>289</hi> b. n. <hi>30</hi> A. D. <hi>1105</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Anno milleſimo cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſimo quinto, Rex Anglorum Henricus tranſiit mare, omnes autem pene majores-Normannorum ad ejus adventum, ſpreto comite Domino ſuo, cui fidelitatem jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verant, in aurum &amp; argentum regis, quod ipſe de Anglia portaverat cucurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, eique caſtra munitaſque civitatis tradiderunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was the way in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and from thence brought hither, when any Earl or great Man found himſelf grieved by another, injured, or highly affronted, they frequently got together all their Men at Arms, their other Tenants, and poor Dependants, and as much Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from their Friends and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates as they could, and burnt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Caſtles or Houſes, deſtroyed their Lands and ſmall Territories, and carried away the Inhabitants Priſoners. The <hi>Norman</hi> Hiſtories abound with theſe Stories. <hi>Ordericus Vitalis,</hi> in the Lives of <hi>Rufus, Henry</hi> I. and this King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> eſpecially, hath many Relations of ſuch inhumane Ravages. And even at this very time, the <hi>Norman</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Soldiers, and other Foreigners, as well of <hi>Maud</hi>'s, as <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Party, practiſed the ſame Barbarities in this Nation: The Country, or Husbandmen, ſuch as ploughed and ſowed, ſuch as cultivated Towns and Villages, and the Inhabitants thereof, were given to the Soldiers as their Wages, and were ſold with their Goods and Subſtance.<note place="margin">Contin. ad Flor. Wig. f. <hi>672.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus in ſtipendium dantur, &amp; venundun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vicorum &amp; villarum cultores &amp; habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores, cum rebus ſuis univerſis, ac ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cambden. Brit f. <hi>199 200.</hi>
                     </note> In this King's Reign there were in <hi>England</hi> ſo many Tyrants, as there were Lords of Caſtles; and many <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings</hi> and <hi>Britains</hi> flocked to him from beyond Sea, who were accuſtomed to live by plundering, that came into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in expectation of geat Booty.<note place="margin">Malmsb. fol. <hi>105.</hi> a. n. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Sub Stephano plures ex Flandria &amp; Britannia, rapto vivere aſſueti, ſpe magnarum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darum Angliam involabant. England</hi> was then made a Prey to all Invaders and Villains.</p>
                  <p>But the Author tells us, that <hi>the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Good of theſe inhumane People did give an equitable Senſe to the Oaths then taken.</hi> If it were not as he ſays, there muſt be Perjury on all ſides; for thoſe who had firſt ſworn to <hi>Maud,</hi> could not transfer their Allegiance on any other Account, (that is, of the <hi>general Good,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59535:16"/> &amp;c.</hi>) either to <hi>Stephen,</hi> or <hi>Henry</hi> II. du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Life. What was thought of the <hi>Perjury</hi> of thoſe Times, and eſpecially of the <hi>Perjury</hi> of his three Biſhops, (who were all <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmans,</hi>) which the Author calls transferring of Allegiance, will be evident from the following Teſtimonies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">f. <hi>221.</hi> a. n. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntington,</hi> who lived and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ote at this time, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his H ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry only unto the Year 1154, tells his Readers, That in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the moſt fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gitious time, in which the Rage of the <hi>Norman</hi> Fury ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, whatſoever <hi>Henry</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannically, or royally, in compariſon of worſe things, ſeemed to have been the beſt; for immediately upon his death, <hi>Stephen, (Vir magnae ſtrenuitatis &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,)</hi> a Man of great Confidence and Boldneſs, though he had ſworn Fealty to the Daughter of King <hi>H nry, (fretus tamen vigore &amp; imp dentia,)</hi> furniſhed with R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> olution and Impudence, <hi>(regna d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ma D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um tenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s invaſit,)</hi> temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing God,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>6.</hi> lin. <hi>1,</hi> &amp;c.</note> invaded the Crown. <hi>But alas!</hi> Wil iam <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>who fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt made Oath to the Daughter of</hi> Henry, <hi>cr wned him; for which Act, God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>gment for him, which he had done to the High Prieſt</hi> Jeremias, <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat is to ſay,) that he ſhould not live a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> after.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gul. Neub. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>4</hi> p. <hi>18, 19.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Cum ergo, ut praedictum eſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ex ld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ricus ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſſet idem Stephanus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> q <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ae ejus de conſervanda fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tate p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aeſticerat, p aevaricator reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m arripuit.</hi> Therefore, as hath b en ſaid, when K ng <hi>Henry</hi> died, <hi>Stephen</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke his Oath of Fealty made to his Daught r, and ſeized the Kingdoms; the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ps and great Men, that were bound by the ſame O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, giving their Aſſi ance: <hi>Archiepiſcopus q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>idem, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m (ut creditur) perjuria merito, ipſo pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>varicationas anno defecit:</hi> And truly the Archbiſhop, as it was believed, for the ſame C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me of Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jury left the World within a Year.<note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Stephanus ergo. ut contra jus humanum pariter &amp; divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m; huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>icet, quia legitimus heres non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat; &amp; divinum, id eſt violata jurisjuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di religione, ſublimaretur in regem; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eſt quaecunque praeſules &amp; proceres exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere voluerunt. Stephen</hi> therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was made King againſt both humane and divine Laws; humane, as not being the lawful Heir; divine, as having violated his Oath; promiſed and agreed to do whatſoever the Biſhops and Great Men exacted of him.</p>
                  <p>As to <hi>Roger</hi> Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>isbury,</hi> if we may believe <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> he ſware to <hi>Maud</hi> what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he never intended to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. The Teſtimony is from what the Hi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orian heard him ſay:<note place="margin">Malmsb. f <hi>99.</hi> b. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ego Rogerium Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>esberienſem Epiſcopum ſaep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e aud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, ſolutum ſe a Sacramento, quod Imperatrici fecerat, &amp;c.</hi> I have often heard <hi>R ger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſay, he was free from the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th he had made to the Empreſs <hi>beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe he made it upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that the King ſhould not marry his Daughter to a Stranger, out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Nec vero haec ita dixerim, quod credam vera fuiſſe verba hominus, qui ſe unicu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>que tempori, pro volubilitate fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae accommodare noſſet</hi> Neither have I ſaid theſe things, that I b lieve the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n's Words to be true, who knew how to comply with all Times, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date himſelf to every Turn of Fortune. This <hi>Roger</hi> was an illiterate P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieſt,<note place="margin">Gul. Neub. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> who got his Living by his ſaying M ſs in the Suburbs of <hi>Caen,</hi> in <hi>Norma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dy.</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> took him to be his Chaplain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was ready at h s Office, and a cunning, crafty Man, and promoted him to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y;</hi> and not only ſo, but committed to him the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Adminiſtration of Secular Affairs: <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t eſſet non tantum in Eccleſia magnus, ſed etiam in regno a rege ſecundus:</hi> So as he was not only great in the Church, but ſecond, or next to the King, in the Kingdom. <hi>Sed r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge defuncto,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>qui ei tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae in ſeculo claritatis author extiterat, circa legitimos ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s haeredes infid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s; ut Stephanum ſacramento illo aeque aſtrictum alliceret, non eſt veritus incurrere perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m etiam aliis inſigne pej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di praeſtruxit exemplum.</hi> But the King
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59535:16"/> being dead, who had made him ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the World, he proved unfaithful to his lawful Heirs; that he might pleaſe <hi>Stephen,</hi> who was bound by the ſame Oath, did not only commit Perjury him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but became a famous Example to others to do the like.</p>
                  <p>As to the Third, <hi>Henry</hi> Biſhop of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncheſter,</hi> the <hi>Pope's Legat,</hi> who was firſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de Abbot of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſtenbury,</hi> and then p omoted to that See by K ng <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> There needs no more to be ſaid of him, than that he firſt ſware to be true to <hi>Maud,</hi> and to maintain her Title af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Father's death; yet uſed all the Endeavour that he could, to ſet up his Brother <hi>Stephen,</hi> by making the Clergy (who then ruled all) for him, and then ſware to be true to him. When <hi>Stephen</hi> was beaten, and made Priſoner by <hi>Maud,</hi> he lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him, and ſware again to <hi>Maud;</hi> and when he was at liberty, he left <hi>Maud,</hi> and made Oath of Fealty to him again, and continued <hi>Pope's Legat</hi> all the time.</p>
                  <p>The Concluſion of the Anſwer to this Inſtance ſhall be, the Judgment and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> in this very Caſe in his <hi>Concordia Diſcors,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 33, 34.</note> firſt printed 1659 and reprinted, 1683. The perfidious V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olation of the Oath made to <hi>Maud,</hi> in crowning <hi>Stephen</hi> after King <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nry</hi>s death, brought exemplary Judgments on the wilful Violators thereof, and a bloody, long, laſting, Civil War, within the Bowels of the Realm, between <hi>Maud,</hi> her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> and the Uſurper <hi>Stephen,</hi> to the great Oppreſſion, Devaſtation and Deſolation of the <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> as our Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> orians obſerve:<note place="margin">Hollinſhed, v. <hi>3.</hi> f. <hi>46.</hi>
                     </note> All the <hi>Good</hi> they hoped for, by diſinheriting <hi>Maud,</hi> and crowning <hi>Stephen,</hi> upon their own Terms, againſt <hi>his own,</hi> and <hi>their Oaths,</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void and null by his Perfidiouſneſs, through Divine Juſtice, which will <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> permit any <hi>good</hi> things to ſpring out of ſuch enormous Evils as <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Treachery;</hi> which produced ſundry Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Civil Wars; never ceaſing, till <hi>Henry,</hi> the right Heir, was reſtored to the Crown by a friendly Agreement; the only probable ſpeedy way now, to end our preſent Wars, oppreſſions, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Military Government, and reſtore Peace and Proſperity in our Nations.</p>
                  <p>As to his Inſtance about Oaths taken during the Controverſies between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> a true Tranſcript of the Parliament-Rolls will be the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt and plaineſt Anſwer; which here follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memorand.</hi> that the xvj day of <hi>Octobre,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>39</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> the ix day of this preſent Parlement, The Counſeill of the right high, and mighty Prince, <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Parlement chambre a Writeing, conteigning the cleyme and title of the right, that the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> pretended unto the Coro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the ſame Writeing delivered to the right reverent fadre in God <hi>George</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtre, Chauncellour</hi> of <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ond,</hi> deſiring him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſame writeing might be ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed to the Lordes Spirituelx and Temporelx aſſembled in this preſent Parlement, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d that the ſeid <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c</hi> myght have brief and exp dient anſwere thereof; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppon the ſeid <hi>Chauncellour</hi> opened and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wed the ſeid deſire to the Lordes Spirituelx and Temporelx, askyng the Queſ ion of theym whether they wold the ſeid writeing ſhuld be openly radde before them or noo. To the which Queſtion it was anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red and agreed by all the ſeid Lordes. Inaſmuch as every perſone high and lowe, ſaying to this high Court of Parlement muſt be herd, and his deſire and peticion underſtand, that the ſeid writeing ſhuld be radde and herde, <hi>not to be anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>red without the King's Commaundement, for ſo much as the matter is ſo high, and of ſo grete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ght and poyſe,</hi> which writeing there than was radde; The tenour whereof followeth in theſe words: <hi>It is not to be forgotten,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 11.</note> &amp;c. as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 19. followeth.</p>
                  <p>And afterward the xvij day of <hi>Octobre,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 12.</note> the x day of this preſent Parlement, the ſeid <hi>Chauncellour</hi> ſhewed and declare to the ſeid Lords Spirituelx and Temporelx,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59535:17"/> being in the ſame Parlement, how that the Counſeill of the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> gretly deſired to have anſwer of ſuch writeing, as upon the xvj day of <hi>Octobre</hi> laſt paſſed was put into this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, on the behalf of the ſeid <hi>Duc;</hi> and thereupon asked the ſeid Lordes what they thought was to be doon in that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tier. To the which Queſtion it was anſwered and thought by all the ſaid Lordes, <hi>That the matter was ſo high, and of ſuch might, that it was not to eny of the King's S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s to enter into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication thereof, without his high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, agreement, and aſſent had therto.</hi> And fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmore foraſmuch as the ſeid <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſired and required brief and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>aied anſwere of the ſeid wryte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in eſchneing and avoyding of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ete and manyfold inconveniences, that weren lykly to enſue, if haſtly proviſion of good anſwere in that behalfe were not had; it was thought and agreed by all the Lordes, that they all ſhuld goe unto the King to declare and open the ſeid matier unto h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Highneſs, <hi>and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what his good G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ace wold to be doon ſe ther therin.</hi> And the uppon inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent all the ſeid Lordes Spirituelx and Temporelx went unto the King's high p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence, and therunto open<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed the ſeid mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er by the mouth of his ſeid <hi>Chauncellour</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and the ſeid mate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r by the King's Highneſs herd and conceyved, <hi>It pleaſed him to pray and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mmand all the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Lordes, that they ſhuld ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>che for to fynde, in as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch as in them was, all ſuch things as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght be objecte and laide a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enſt the cleyme a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> title of the ſeid Duc.</hi> And the ſeid L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdes b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aught the King, that he wold remember him, yf he myght fynd eny reſonable matier that myght be objected ayenſt the ſeid cleym and title, in ſo moche as his ſeid Highneſs had ſeen and underſtonden many divers Writeings and Chronicles; wheruppon on the morne, the xviij day of <hi>Octobre,</hi> the xj day of this preſent Parlement, <hi>the foreſeid Lordes ſent for the King's Juſtices into the Parlement-chambre, to have their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis and Counſeill in this behalf;</hi> and there delivered to them the writeing of the cleyme of the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and in the King's name gave them ſtraitely in commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, ſadly to take aviſament therin, And to ſerche and find all ſuch obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as myght be leyde ayenſt the ſame in fortefying of the King's right.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto <hi>the ſame Juſtices,</hi> the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> the xx day of <hi>Octobre</hi> then next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, for their aunſwere upon the ſeid writeing to them delivered ſeiden, that they were the King's Juſtices, and have to determine ſuch matiers as come before them in the Law; between partie and partie they mey not be of Counſeill: An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſith this matier was betweene the <hi>King</hi> and the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> as two pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties, and alſo it hath not be accuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to calle the Juſtices to Counſeill in ſuch matiers; <hi>and in eſpeciall the matier was ſo high, and touched the King's high Eſtate and Regalie, which is above the law, and paſſed their lerning, wherefore they durſt not enter into eny communication thereof,</hi> for it <hi>perteyned</hi> to the Lordes of the King's blode, and thapparage of this his lond, to have communication and medle in ſuch matiers; And therefore they humble by ſought all the Lordes, to have them <hi>utterly excuſed</hi> of any avyce or counſeill by them to be yeven in that matier.</p>
                  <p>And then the ſeid Lordes conſidering the aunſwere of the ſeid <hi>Juges,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have the avice and good counſeill of all the K ng's Counſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llours, ſent for all the King's <hi>Sergeau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts,</hi> and <hi>Attournay,</hi> and gave theym ſtraight commaundement in the King's name, <hi>that they ſadly and aviſely ſhuld ſerche and ſeke all ſuch things, as might be beſt and ſtrengest to be allegged for the King's availe, in objection and deferyng of the ſeid title and cleyme of the ſeid Duc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereunto the ſeid <hi>Sergeaunts</hi> and <hi>Attourney,</hi> the <hi>Wenſday</hi> then next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring, anſwered and ſeiden, that the ſeid matier was put unto the King's
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59535:17"/> 
                     <hi>Juſtices,</hi> and how the <hi>Monday</hi> laſt paſſed the ſame <hi>Juſtices</hi> ſeiden, and declared to the ſeid Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des, that the ſeid matier was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo high, and of ſo great wight, that it paſſed ther lerning; and alſo they durſt not enter eny communication in that matier, to yeve any avyce or counſaill therein: <hi>And ſi h that the ſaid matier was ſo high, that it paſſed the lerning of the Juſtices, it muſt needs excede ther lerning; and alſo they durſt not enter eny communication in that matter,</hi> and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and beſought all the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to have them excuſed of yevyng eny avyce or counſaill therin.</p>
                  <p>To whom it was aunſwered, by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avys of all the Lordes, by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler,</hi> that they mygh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not ſo be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for they were the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng's pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticuler Counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illers, and therfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y had ther fees and wages: And as to that the ſeid <hi>Sergeaunts</hi> and <hi>Attourney</hi> ſeiden, that they were the King's Counſaillers in the Law, in ſuch things as were under his auctorite, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Commiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n; <hi>but this mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er was above his auct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ite, wherin they myght not medle,</hi> and humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the ſeid Lordes to have them excu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed of yevyng eny counſaill in that matier: and it was aunſwered them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn, that the Lordes wuld not hold them excuſed, but let the King's High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have knowleche what they ſaid; and theruppon the ſeid <hi>Chaunceller</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the Lordes Spirituelx and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perelx of the ſeyings and excuſes of the <hi>Juſtices,</hi> and ſeyings and excuſes of the <hi>Sergeaunts</hi> and <hi>Attourney, and alſo the grete commaundement of the King's High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they had, to find all ſuch obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as myght be mooſt mighty to defend the King's right and title, and to defete the title and cleyme of the ſeid Duk of</hi> York; And alſo that the King myght underſtond, that the ſeid Lordes diden their true and faithful devoire and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall in the ſeid matier, <hi>deſired all the Lordes that every of them ſhuld ſey what he cowed ſey in fortefying the King's title, and in defeteing of the cleyme of the ſeid Duc:</hi> And than it was <hi>agreed</hi> by all the Lordes, that every Lorde ſhuld have his fredome to ſey wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t he wold ſey, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eny reporting or magre to be had for his ſeying; And theruppon after the ſeiyng of all the Lordes every after other, It was concluded that thes matiers and articles, here undrewriten, ſhuld be aleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and objecte ayenſt the ſeid cleyme and title of the ſeid <hi>Duc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is thought,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Objectio contra ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum.</note> that the Lordes of this Lond muſt needs call to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunces, <hi>the grete othes the which they have made to the King our Soveraigne Lorde,</hi> the which may be leyde to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſeid <hi>Due</hi> of <hi>York;</hi> and that the Lordes <hi>may not breke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o othes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item.</hi> It is thought alſo, that it is to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be called to remembraunce the grete and notable <hi>Acts of Parlements,</hi> made in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Parlements of divers of the King's Progeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>urs, The which Acts be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and reſonable to be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yd againe the title of the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York.</hi> The which Acts been of moche more auctorite than eny Cronicle, <hi>And alſo of auctorite to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fete eny manner of title be made to eny perſone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> It is thought, that there is to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> be leyd agayn the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id title <hi>divers entaills made to the heires males,</hi> as for the <hi>Corone</hi> of <hi>Englond,</hi> as it may appere by divers Cronicles and Parlements.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> It is thought, yf the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſhu'd make eny title or cleyme by the Lyne of Sir <hi>Leonell,</hi> that the ſame <hi>Duc</hi> ſhuld bere the Armes of the ſame <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell,</hi> and not the Armes of <hi>Edmund Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> late <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> It is to be allegged agen the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> title of the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> that the time that King <hi>Herry</hi> the fourth toke upon him the <hi>Corone</hi> of <hi>Englond, he ſaid he entred and toke upon him the Corone as right en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriter to King</hi> Herry <hi>the third, and not as a Conquerour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the which Articles the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> gave his anſweres in writeing as folowen.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59535:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reſponſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes praefati Ducis ad Objectiones tituli ſui praedicti.</note>Here under folowen the anſweres of <hi>Richard Plantagenet,</hi> called comonly <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York, &amp;c.</hi> to certain raiſons and colours alleged, as it is ſaid, ayenſt the matier of his right and title, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Where it is ſaid, that it is thought,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 14.</note> that the Lordes muſt nedes calle to their remembraunce the <hi>grete Othes which they have made to the King,</hi> which may be leid to the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and that they may not breke thoo othes.</p>
                  <p>The ſeid <hi>Richard</hi> aunſwereth and ſaith, that every man, under the peyne of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting dampnation, is bounde to obey to the lawe and commaundements of God, by the which lawe and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements trouth and juſtice owe to be preferred and obſerved, and untrouth and injuſtice laid apart and repreſſed, and ſoe it is that of this bond, and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of obedyence to Godd's lawe, <hi>noo man may diſcharge himſelf by his owne deede or act, promiſe or ooth,</hi> for elles of the contrary wold enſue <hi>innumerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences;</hi> wherefore ſith it is ſoe, that the matier of the title and cleyme of the ſeid <hi>Richard Plantagenet</hi> is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, and lawful, and grounded upon evident trouth and juſtice; It followeth, that man ſhuld have rather conſideration to trouth, right and juſtice in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier accordingly with the will of the law of God, then to any promiſſe or ooth made by him to the contrarie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered namely that by the lawe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of holy Churche an ooth made by oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perſone unto the prejudice or hurt of an other, contrarie to trouth, juſtice and charity, in the which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the plenitude and perfection of Godd's lawe, is void and of noon effect, neither in eny wiſe obligatory; And that the vertue and nature of an ooth <hi>is to confirm trouth, and in no wyſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne it;</hi> And over that <hi>by the ooth of feaute, homage, or ligeaunce, no man is bounden to any inconvenient or unlawfull thing;</hi> And how be it that this anſwer is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uffiſaunt to all maner objections that may be made ayenſt his cleyme and entent in this partie by reaſon or occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any ooth, yet natheleſs the ſeid <hi>Richard,</hi> for as much as the matier of othes is a matier ſpirituell, for more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of his conſcience, honeſty and trouth in this partie, offreth himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to aunſwer b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore any Juge Spirituell, competent in place, and tyme covenable to all maner of men, that any thing woll purpoſe ayenſt him in that behalf.</p>
                  <p>And to ſhew clerely, <hi>that lawfully withouten offence of God and conſcience he may cleyme and purſue his right, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Juſtice, in ſuch fourme as he dooth, and that all other perſones, and namely the Peers and Lordes of this Reame may, and by the law of God and man ought to helpe, and aſſiſt him in trouth and juſtice, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any ooth of feaute, or other by him or them here before made.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Over this, where it is thought alſo,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 15.</note> that it is to be called to remembraunce the <hi>grete and notable Acts of Parlement,</hi> made in dyvers Parlements of dyvers of the King's progenitours, the which actes been ſufficient to be leyed ayenſt the title of the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and of more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite then eny Cronicle, And alſoe of auctorite to defete any maner title made to eny perſone.</p>
                  <p>And alſo where 'tis ſaid, that it is to be leyde ayenſt the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e title dyvers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailles made to the heirs males, as for the <hi>Corone</hi> of <hi>Englond,</hi> as it may appear by divers Cronicles and Parlements,</p>
                  <p>The ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id <hi>Richard Plantagin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</hi> aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and ſaith, that in trouth ther been noo ſuch actes and tailles made by eny Parlement herebefore, as it is ſurmyſed, <hi>but only in the vijth year of King</hi> Herry <hi>the fourth a certeyne act and ordinaunce was made in a Parlement, by him called, wherein he made the Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mes of</hi> Englond <hi>and</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aunce, <hi>amongs others, to be unto him, and to the heirs of his body comyng, and to his iiij ſonnes, and the heires of their bodies commyng, in maner and forme as it appereth in the ſame act;</hi> And if he myght have obteigned and rejoyſed the ſeid Corones, <hi>&amp;c. by title of inheritaunce,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59535:18"/> diſcent, or ſucceſſion,</hi> he neither neded, nor wold have deſired, or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de them to be graunted to him in ſuch wiſe, as they be by the ſeid acte, <hi>The which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no place, nother is of eny force or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ayenſt him, that is right enheritor of the ſeid Corones, as it accordeth with Godd's lawe, and all natural lawes; how it be that all other actes and ordinaunces made in the ſeid Parlement, and ſithen been good and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffiſant ayenſt all other perſones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 16.</note>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> Where it is thought, that if the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> ſhuld make any title or cleyme by the line of Sir <hi>Leonell,</hi> he ſhuld bere the Armes of the ſame Sir <hi>Leonell,</hi> and not the Armes of <hi>Edmund Langley</hi> late <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>k.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> aunſwereth, and ſaith, that trouth is, he myght lawfully have borne the Armes of the ſeid Sir <hi>Leonell</hi> here biſore, and alſo the ſame Armes that King <hi>Edward</hi> the third bare, that is to ſay the Armes of the Reaumes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> but he abſteyned of beryng of the ſeid Armes, <hi>like as he abſteigned for the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me of purpoſyng, and purſuing of his right and title,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for cauſes not inknowen to all this Reaume; for though right for a time reſt, and bee put to ſcilence, yet it roteth not, ner ſhall not periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 17.</note>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> Where it is alleged ayenſt the title of the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> that the ſeid <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Derby,</hi> at ſuch tyme as he toke uppon him the <hi>Corone</hi> of <hi>Englond,</hi> ſaid, that he entred and toke the ſame <hi>Corone</hi> uppon him as right enheritour to King <hi>Herry</hi> the third, and not as a <hi>Conquerour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> therto ſaith, that ſuch ſaying of the ſeid King <hi>Herry</hi> the fourth may in noo wiſe be true, and that the contrarie therof, which is trouth, ſhall be largely ynough ſhewed, approved, and juſtefyed by ſufficiaunt auctorite, and matier of record: <hi>And over that, that his ſeid ſaying, was oonly to ſhadow, and colour fraudulently his ſeid unright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, and violent uſurpation, And by that moyen to abuſe deceyvably the people ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding about him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> The <hi>Saturday,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 18.</note> the xvij day of this preſent Parlement, it was ſhewed unto the Lords Spirituelx and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relx, being in this preſent Parlement, by the mouth of the ſeid <hi>Chaunceller,</hi> that the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> called beſily, to have haſty and ſpedy aunſwere of ſuch matiers, as touched his title aboveſeid; <hi>And how that for as moche as it is thought by all the Lordes, that the title of the ſeid Duc cannot be defeted; and in eſchewing of the grete inconvenients that may enſue, a meane was found to ſave the King's honour and aſtate, and to appeaſe the ſeid Duc if he wold,</hi> which is this; That the King ſhall keep the Corones, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtate, and dignity roiall, duryng his lyfe, and the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and his heirs, to ſuccede him in the ſame; Exhorting and ſtering all the ſeid Lordes, that if eny of them cowde finde eny other or better meane, that it might be ſhewed; whereuppon after ſad and ripe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication in this matier had, <hi>it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and agreed by all the ſeid Lordes, that ſith it was ſoo, that the title of the ſeid</hi> Duc <hi>of</hi> York <hi>cannot be defeted, and in eſchuing the grete inconvenients that myght enſue, to take the meane above-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed, The othes that the ſeid Lordes had made unto the King's Highneſs at</hi> Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, <hi>and other places ſaved, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences therin clered;</hi> and over that it was agreed by the ſeid Lordes, that the ſeid meane ſhuld be opened and declared to the King's Highneſs: And forthwith they went towards the King, where he was in his Chambre, within his Palice of <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and in their goyng out of the Parlement-chambre, the ſeid <hi>Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler</hi> asked of the ſeid Lordes, that ſith it was ſoo, that the ſeid mean ſhuld be opened by his mouth to the King's good Grace, yf they wold abide by him how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever that the King toke the matier, and all they aunſwered and ſaid, Yee.</p>
                  <p>All theſe premiſſes thus ſhewed and opened to the King's Highneſs, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with the grace of the Holy Gooſt, and in eſchuying of effuſion of Chriſtien
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59535:19"/> blode, by goode and ſad deliveration, and avyce had with all his Lordes Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuelx and Temporelx, condeſcended to acord to be made betweene him, and the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and to be auctorized by thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoryte of this preſent Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lement; The tenour of which accord hereafter enſueth in maner and forme following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Concordia facta inter Regem &amp; p aefatum D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cem. n. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note>Bleſſed be <hi>Jeſu,</hi> in whos hand and bountie reſtith, and is the peas and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee betwixt Princes, and the wele of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reaume; thurgh whos direction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed it is, appointed, and accorded as followeth, Betwixt the mooſt mighty Prynce, King <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rry</hi> the ſext, King of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and Lorde of <hi>Irelond,</hi> on that oon partie; and the right high, and mighty Prince, <hi>Richard Plan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aginet, Duc</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> on that other partie, upon certaine matiers of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaunce moeved betwixt them, and in eſpeciall upon the cleyme and title unto the <hi>Corones</hi> of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and roiall power, eſtate, and dignite ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteigning to the ſame, and Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond,</hi> opened, ſhewed, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſeid <hi>Duc</hi> afore all the Lordes Spirituelx and Temperelx, being in this preſent Parlement, <hi>The ſeid agrement, appointment, and accord to be auctoriſed by the ſame Parlement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">This is the ſame <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim</hi> with the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting put in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>n.</hi> 11.</note>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Where the ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> hath declared, and opened as above, his ſeid title and cleyme in manere as followeth; That the right noble, and worthy Prince, <hi>Herry,</hi> King of <hi>Englond,</hi> the third, had iſſue, and leefully gate <hi>Edward</hi> his firſt begoten Sonne, born at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the XV <hi>Kalends</hi> of <hi>Juyll,</hi> in the <hi>Vigill</hi> of St. <hi>Marc</hi> and <hi>Mercellian,</hi> the yere of our Lorde MCCXXXIX. and <hi>Edmund</hi> his ſecund Sonne, which was borne on St. <hi>Marcell</hi> day, the yere of our Lorde MCCXLV. The which <hi>Edward,</hi> af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er the deth of the ſeid King <hi>Herry</hi> his Fader, entitled and called King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, had Iſſue <hi>Edward</hi> his fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> begotten Son, entitled and called, after the deceſſe of the ſeid firſt <hi>Edward</hi> his fader, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecund; which had Iſſue, and leefully gate the right noble, and honourable Prynce, <hi>Edward</hi> the third, the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and Lorde of <hi>Irelond;</hi> which <hi>Edward</hi> the third, true and undoubted King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and Lorde of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond,</hi> had Iſſue and leefully gate <hi>Edward</hi> his firſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>goten ſonne, <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales, William Hatfeld</hi> ſecund begotten, <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> third begoten <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>Clarence, John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> fourth begoten <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Edmund Langley</hi> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h goten <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>Yorke, Thomas W d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtoke</hi> ſixt goten <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>Gloue,</hi> and <hi>William Windſore</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth goten; The ſeid <hi>Edward Prynce</hi> of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es,</hi> which dyed in the lyfe of the ſeid <hi>Edward</hi> King, had Iſſue and leeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gate <hi>Richard,</hi> the which ſucceeded the ſame <hi>Edward</hi> King, his Grauntfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, in roiall Dignite, entitled and called King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecund, and dyed without Iſſue. <hi>William Hatfeld,</hi> the ſecund go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne of the ſeid <hi>Edward</hi> King, dyed without Iſſue. <hi>Leonell,</hi> the third goten ſonne of the ſame <hi>Edward</hi> King, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c</hi> of <hi>Clarence,</hi> had Iſſue, and leefully gate <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lippe</hi> his only daughter and heir, which by the Sacrament of Matrimonie copled unto <hi>Edmund Mortymer Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche,</hi> had Iſſue, and leefully bore <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Mortymer Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche,</hi> his ſonne and hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e; which <hi>Roger Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche</hi> had Iſſue, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fully gate <hi>Edmond Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche, Roger Mortymer, Anne,</hi> and <hi>Alianore;</hi> which <hi>Edmund, Roger,</hi> and <hi>Alianore</hi> dyed without Iſſue, and the ſeid <hi>Anne</hi> under the Sacrament of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie copled unto <hi>Richard Erle</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigge,</hi> the ſonne of the ſeid <hi>Edmund Langley,</hi> the fift goten ſonne of the ſeid King <hi>Edward,</hi> as it is afore ſpecified, had Iſſue, and leefully bare <hi>Richard Plantaginet,</hi> commonly called <hi>Duc</hi> of <hi>York:</hi> The ſeid <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the fourth goten ſonne of the ſeid King <hi>Edward,</hi> and the younger Brother of the ſeid <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell,</hi> had Iſſue, and leefully gate <hi>Henry Erle</hi> of <hi>Derby,</hi> which incontinent, after the time that the ſeid King <hi>Richard</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:59535:19"/> reſigned the <hi>Corones</hi> of the ſeid Reaumes, and the ſeid Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightwiſely entred upon the ſame, then beying on lyve</hi> Edmund Mortymer Erle <hi>of</hi> Marche, <hi>ſonne to</hi> Roger Mortymer Erle <hi>of</hi> Marche, <hi>ſonne and heir of the ſaid</hi> Phelippe, <hi>daughter and heir of the ſeid Sir</hi> Leonell, <hi>the third ſonne of the ſeid King</hi> Edward <hi>the third; to the which</hi> Edmund <hi>the right and title of the ſeid Corones and Lordſhip by lawe and cuſtome belonged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the which <hi>Richard Duc of York,</hi> as ſonne to <hi>Anne,</hi> daughter to <hi>Roger Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymer Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche,</hi> ſonne and heir to the ſeid <hi>Phelippe,</hi> daughter and heir to the ſeid <hi>Leonell,</hi> the third goten ſonne of the ſeid King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, the right title, dignite roiall, and eſtate of the <hi>Corones</hi> of the Reaumes of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of the Lordſhip and lond of <hi>Irelond, of right, lawe, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume apperteigneth, and belongeth, afore eny iſſue of the ſeid</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Gaunt, <hi>the fourth goten ſonne of the ſeid King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 20.</note>The ſeid title natheleſs notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and without prejudice of the ſame, The ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York, tenderly deſireyng the wele, reſt, and proſperite of this lond, and to ſet apart all that, that myght be trouble to the ſame; and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the poſſeſſion of the ſeid King</hi> Herry <hi>the ſixt, and that he hath for his time be named, taken, and reputed King of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond, <hi>and of</hi> Fraunce, <hi>and Lorde of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lond, <hi>is content, agreeth, and conſenteth,</hi> that he be had, reputed, and taken, King of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> with the roiall eſtate, dignite, and pre-emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence belonging therto, and Lord of <hi>Irelond,</hi> duryng his lyfe naturall; and for that time the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> without hurt or prejudice of his ſeid right and title, ſhall take, worſhip, and honour him for his Soveraine Lorde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 22.</note>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> It is accorded, appointed, and agreed, that the ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>k</hi> rejoyſe, be entitled, called, and reputed, from hens forth verrey and rightfull heire to the <hi>Corones,</hi> roiall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, dignite, and Lordſhip aboveſeid; and after the deceſſe of the ſeid King <hi>Herry,</hi> or when he woll ley from him the ſeid <hi>Corones,</hi> eſtate, dignite, and Lordſhip, the ſeid <hi>Duc,</hi> and his heires, ſhall immediately ſucceed to the ſeid <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones,</hi> roiall eſtate, dignite, and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Item,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 25.</note> For the more eſtabliſhing the ſeid accord; It is appointed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that the Lordes Spirituelx and Temporelx, being in this preſent Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oothes to accepte, take, wurſhip, and repute the ſeid <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Due</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> and his ſeid heires, as above is reherced; and kepe, obſerve, and ſtrengthen, in as much as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teigneth unto them, all the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſeid, and reſiſt to their power all them that wull preſume the contrary, according to their eſtates and degrees.</p>
                  <p>The King underſtanding certainly the ſeid title of the ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> juſt, lawful, true, and ſuffiſant;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>n.</hi> 27.</note> by tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis and aſſent of the Lords Spirituelx and Temporelx, and Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlement aſſembled, and by aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the ſame Parlement, declareth, approveth, and ratifieth, confermeth, and accepteth the ſeid title juſt, good, lawfull, and true, and therunto yeveth his aſſent, and agreement, of his f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e will and libertie. And over that, by the ſeid avis and auctorite, declareth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titleth, calleth, ſtabliſheth, affermeth, and reputeth the ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York</hi> verrey, true, and rightfull heire to the <hi>Corones,</hi> roiall eſtate and dignite of the Reaumes of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of the Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond</hi> aforeſeid; and that according to the wurſhip and reverence that therto belongeth, he be taken, accepted, and reputed, in wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and reverence, by all the States of the ſeid Reaume of <hi>Englond,</hi> and of all his Subgetts therof, ſaving and ordeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſame auctorite, the King to have the ſeid <hi>Corones,</hi> Reaumes, roiall, eſtate, dignite, and pre-eminence of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59535:20"/> ſame, and the ſeid Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond,</hi> duryng his lyf naturall. And ferther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, by the ſame avis and auctorite, wolle, conſenteth, and agreeth, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his deceſſe, or when it ſhall pleaſe his Highneſs to ley from him the ſeid <hi>Corones,</hi> eſtate, dignite, and Lordſhip, or therof ceſſeth; The ſeid <hi>Richard Duc</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> and his heires, ſhall ymmediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſucceed him in the ſeid <hi>Corones,</hi> roiall eſtate, dignite, and Lordſhip, and them then have and joy, <hi>any Act of Parlement, Statute, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dynaunce,</hi> or other thing, to the <hi>contrarie made, or interruption, or diſcontinuance of poſſeſſion notwithſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> And moreover, by the ſeid avis and auctorite, ſtabliſheth, graunteth, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fermeth, approveth, ratifieth, and accepteth the ſeid accord, and all things therin conteyned; And thereunto freely and abſolutely aſſenteth, and agreeth.</p>
                  <p>From this Record it is evident,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Richard Duke</hi> of <hi>York</hi> exhibited his bare Claim and Title to the Lords <hi>only.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chard Duke</hi> of <hi>York</hi> did not <hi>peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> the Lords. <hi>n.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. His Council only delivered in a W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iting, containing his Deſcent, and Title by <hi>Birthright,</hi> and <hi>Hereditary Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſion,</hi> and nothing elſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Matter was ſo high, the Lords could not anſwer it, nor enter into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication thereof, without the King's Command, Agreement, and Aſſent.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The King conſented, and prayed and commanded the Lords to ſearch and find out what might be oppoſed to the Duke's Claim and Title.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. They ſent for the Judges, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe what might be ſaid againſt the Duke, to fortifie the King's Right.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Judges excuſed themſelves, for that the matter was ſo high, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King's high Eſtate, and Regality, <hi>which was above the Law,</hi> and paſſed their Learning; wherefore they dare not enter into Communication thereof.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds, upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this Anſwer of the Judges, ſent for the King's Serjeants and Attorney, and gave them the ſame Command, who made the ſame Excuſe the Judges had done; but the Lords would not take it: Whereupon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Reaſons againſt the Duke's Claim and Title were exhibited, <hi>n.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour. <hi>p.</hi> 22, 23.</note> That in the Articles and Reaſons againſt the Duke's Claim and Title, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is not the leaſt word of <hi>Phileppe</hi>'s being illegitimate, or that her F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorc'd from her Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her; nor is there the leaſt mention that the Houſe of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> claimed by Preſcription of ſixty years Poſſeſſion, (which comes from <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eman,</hi> and the Authour is to find out both theſe things in the Parliament Rolls, or be guilty of downright Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; for he reports them both as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt the Duke's Title. As to the firſt, there needed no other Argument, if it had been inſiſted on, and could have been made good: And as to the ſecond, neither was it inſiſted on, or mentioned, as was ſaid before; and if it had, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tempus occurrit Regi</hi> would have been a ſure Rule in this Caſe: For it is abſurd to think that Preſcription, at leaſt ſo ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t a Preſcription as this, could juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a wrong, and make a Title in this Caſe; for there is another Rule of Law, <hi>Non confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>matur Tractu temporis, quod de jure non ſubſiſtit;</hi> no length of time makes that lawfull which was not ſo from the beginning. If there be a right Heir of the Crown, that claims or elſe would claim, but that he wants either notice of his Right and Title, or Power to make it good, or forbears to claim for other ſufficient Reaſons,<note place="margin">Vide n. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> here Preſcription ſignifies nothing.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. It was allowed, at leaſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, that <hi>all Perſons,</hi> and namely the <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> might, and by the Laws or God and Man ought <hi>to help and aſſiſt him in Truth and Juſtice.</hi> n. 14.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. It was the Judgme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of all the Lords, that the Title of the Duke, which was onely Succeſſion by Birthright, and <hi>Proximity of Bloud,</hi> could not be defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59535:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="12">12. That <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> was by King <hi>Henry,</hi> and the Lords, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as very and rightfull Heir to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>own, and that he was ſo to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. That the mean found out to ſave the King's Honour, and appeaſe the Duke, <hi>if he would,</hi> was not, or could be impoſed or forced upon him, but he was at liberty to accept or refuſe it, and was no ways bound, but by his own co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſent <hi>n.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 The Oath that <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rk</hi> took, was in <hi>purſuance</hi> of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; and any man may lawfully take an Oath to make good a Bargain, where no man receives Injury but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and ſo with his conſent that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, any other Perſon concerned in the Agreement, may ſwear to the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 24.</note>Laſtly, The <hi>Weal, Reſt,</hi> and <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> (which the Authour calls the <hi>Publick Good</hi>) followed this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; and the Reaſon was, that the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>own was reſtored to the right Heir; whereupon all Murmuring, Hatred; S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e, and Contention amongſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Evil-will and Contrivances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one another ceaſed.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are all the Inſtances the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour uſeth; yet two are wanting, the Succeſſions of <hi>Edward</hi> III. and <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. but ſeeing he may have peru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Treatiſe, bearing the Title of the <hi>Grand Queſtion,</hi> he may haply be convinced by what the learned Authour hath ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 80, 81 83, 85, 86.</note> 
                     <hi>that they were both <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers; the firſt during his Father's Life, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond from the very time he took upon him Kingſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Authour's Words, <hi>p.</hi> 29, 30.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are three ſorts of Perſons may be ſaid to have Poſſeſſion of the Crown, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, a King</hi> de jure, <hi>and a King</hi> de facto; <hi>and becauſe the Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tewen theſe doth not ſeem to be well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, I ſhall briefly explain it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper is one that comes in by force, and continues by force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A King</hi> de facto <hi>is one, who comes in by conſent of the Nation, but not by virtue of an immediate hereditary right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>A King</hi> de jure <hi>is one, who comes in by Lineal Deſcent as next Heir; and whoſe Right is owned, and recogniſed by the Eſtates of the Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Authour may make what verbal, frivolous Diſtinction he pleaſes between a King <hi>de facto</hi> and an Uſurper, yet <hi>de facto</hi> they are the very ſame. Let him ſhew an Example in this Nation, if he can, of a King <hi>de facto</hi> ſet up without an Army or Force; or of an Uſurper that came in by Force, who did not make the Nation own him; and though he took upon him the Name and Title by force, and the aſſiſtance of a Party, yet afterwards made the States and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conſent to it. Was not <hi>Edward</hi> II. made Priſoner by an Army, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward depoſed; and <hi>Edward</hi> III. in his Father's lifetime, ſet up by ſuch as were under the power of that Army? And <hi>Henry</hi> IV. ſet up by ſuch as acted, and were under the power of that Force? Our Laws make no difference betwen an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and a King <hi>de facto</hi> according to the Author's deſcription.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Author's Words, <hi>pag.</hi> 32.</head>
                  <p>A King <hi>de facto,</hi> according to our Law, (as I ſaid,) is one in quiet poſſeſſion of the Crown, by Conſent of Parliament, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hereditary Right; ſuch as <hi>Henry IV. V. VI. VII.</hi> were all thought to be by thoſe who made this Diſtinction. For, as far as I can find, the Diſtinction of a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de jure,</hi> was then ſtarted, when the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> ſo much inſiſted on their hereditary Right, and ſo many of our Kings had governed the Kingdom by Conſent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; therefore the Lawyers, to find a ſufficient <hi>Salvo</hi> for the Kings of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> framed this Diſtinction of Kings <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de jure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59535:21"/>
                  <head>Records, Law, and Hiſtory.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>1.</hi> Ed. <hi>IV.</hi> n. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note>In the Firſt of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons exhibit a Petition in Parliament, wherein they ſet forth his Title by <hi>Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> and <hi>Proximity of Blood;</hi> and ſay, <hi>Richard</hi> II. was <hi>lawfully, rightly,</hi> and <hi>juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſeated and poſſeſſed of the <hi>Corone</hi> of <hi>Englond,</hi> Roiall Power, Eſtate, Dignite, Pre-eminence, Governaunce, and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Irelond,</hi> and the ſame joyed in reſt and quiet, without interruption or moleſtation,<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> unto the time that <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> late <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le</hi> of <hi>Derby,</hi> ſonne of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the fourth goten ſonne of King <hi>Edward</hi> III. and younger brother of <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, temerouſly, ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſt rightwiſeneſs, and juſtice,</hi> by force and armes, <hi>ayenſt his fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th and ligeance, rered-werre</hi> at <hi>Flynt</hi> in <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>les, ayenſt the ſeid King</hi> Richard; him toke, and imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſoned in the Towre of <hi>London</hi> of grete violence. And the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King <hi>Richard</hi> ſo being in priſon, and lyvying, <hi>uſurped</hi> and <hi>intruded</hi> upon the Roiall Power, Eſtate, Dignity, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence, poſſeſſions, and Lordſhips a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſeid; taking upon him <hi>uſurpouſly</hi> the <hi>Corone</hi> and <hi>name</hi> of <hi>King</hi> and Lord of the ſame Reaume and Lordſhip; and not therwith ſatisfied or content, but more grevous thyng attempting wykidly, of an unnatural, unmanly, and cruel Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, the ſame King <hi>Richard,</hi> King e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted, coroned, and conſecrate, and <hi>his Liege</hi> and moſt high Lord in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, ayenſt <hi>God's Law, Manne's Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch of Fidelite,</hi> with utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icion attormenting, murdered with moſt vyle, heynous, and lamentable death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note>And that the ſame <hi>Henry unrightwiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ayenſt Lawe,</hi> Conſcience, <hi>and Cuſtume of the ſeid Reaume of</hi> Englond, <hi>uſurped</hi> upon the ſeid Corone and Lordſhip. And that he, and alſo <hi>Henry,</hi> late called King <hi>Henry</hi> V. his ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and the ſeid <hi>Henry,</hi> late called King <hi>Henry</hi> VI. the ſonne of the ſeid <hi>Henry,</hi> late called King <hi>Henry</hi> V. <hi>occupied</hi> the ſeid Reaume of <hi>Englond,</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond,</hi> and <hi>exerciſed</hi> the governaunce therof by <hi>unrightwiſe intruſion,</hi> and <hi>uſurpation,</hi> and in <hi>noon otherwiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis true, the Diſtinction of a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>de jure,</hi> was firſt heard of in this very Parliament, which declared the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Right of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> in in the Firſt of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. in print; which agrees with the Record in the Parliament-Roll, <hi>n.</hi> 41. and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but not ſtarted then by the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d a <hi>ſufficient Salvo</hi> for the Kings of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter;</hi> but an Expreſſion intended by Parliament (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they uſed it) to denote and make known an unlawful, pretended, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng, that had not obtained the Crown by juſt Title; or to ſignifie an Uſurper, by way of <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> or Contradiſtinction to a K ng <hi>de jure,</hi> or in Right. For this very Parliament, that had declared <hi>Henry</hi> IV. V. VI. Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, calls them all, in this Act, or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Kings <hi>de facto;</hi> or in Deed, and not in Right; and their Reigns, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reigns; and very often affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ms them to be but pretenſed Kings, ſuch as did not reign lawfully, nor poſſeſs the Crown by juſt Title. And that this was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Parliament in the uſe of this Expreſſion, the Statute it ſelf will inform the Author, or any indifferent Reader that will peruſe it.</p>
                  <p>The Lawyers did not comment or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcant upon theſe Words, or declare what power a King <hi>de facto</hi> had, before <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Term, in the Ninth of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. and then they acknowledge <hi>Henry</hi> VI. King <hi>de facto</hi> in the Inſtance, to have been an Uſurper, and that he was not King, <hi>forſque per uſurpacion,</hi> but by Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This Ninth of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. was a troubleſome Year, and Make-king <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> in all probability, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Nobility, were at this very time contriving againſt him, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inthrone King <hi>Henry;</hi> for in <hi>July</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing he was in ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rebellion againſt King <hi>Edward,</hi> and about the end of that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59535:21"/> Month, or beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him Priſoner; who ſoon made his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, left the Nation, and went into <hi>Holland, &amp;c</hi> and on the ſixth of <hi>October,</hi> in that Year, <hi>Henry</hi> VI. was reſtored. The Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> was popular, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beyond Imagination; and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Lawyers, during the Contrivance, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſaw the People move that way, might ſtart ſuch Notions about the Power of a King <hi>de facto,</hi> as might encourage the Undertaking of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>wick</hi> and his Friends, for <hi>Henry</hi> VI. againſt <hi>Edward</hi> IV. 'Tis obſervable, that the Judges did not argue, or give any Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in this Caſe, but only the Serjeants and Apprentices of the Law, as appears in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe it ſelf.<note place="margin">Third In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. fol. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> hath out-done the <hi>Year-Book,</hi> 9. <hi>Ed.</hi> IV. <hi>Term. Paſch.</hi> concerning whole Opinion, the Author may read Mr. <hi>Pryn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>482,</hi> &amp;c.</note> in his <hi>Plea for the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe of Lords.</hi> This is a brief Account of a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of the Expreſſion; by which it is moſt manifeſt, that by the Parliament-Roll, the Statute and Caſe of the Ninth of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. he is no other than a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed, unlawful King, and an Uſurper, though ſet up as the three <hi>Henries</hi> were; and therefore the pretended Diſtinction is idle, as may alſo further appear by the following Statute; which, becauſe not common, is here recited at large.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Statutes at large, <hi>17.</hi> Ed. <hi>IV.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Item,</hi> Whereas in the moſt dolorous Abſence of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Soveraign Lord the King out of this his Realm, being in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Holland,</hi> and before his victorious <hi>Regreſs</hi> into the ſame Realm,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 17. <hi>Ed.</hi> IV. <hi>n.</hi> 34 This Writ of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is dated, 15. <hi>Octobr. Rot. Cl.</hi> 49. <hi>Hen.</hi> VI. <hi>M.</hi> 6. <hi>Dorſ.</hi>
                     </note> in a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed Parliament unlawfully, and by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped Power, ſummoned by the Rebel and Enemy to our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> Henry <hi>VI. late in Deed, and not of Right, King of</hi> England, holden in the Palace of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 26th Day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the Ninth Year of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord the King that now is, under the <hi>coloured Title</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Henry,</hi> the Forty ninth Year of the Incoation of his pretenſed Reign, and the Firſt Year of the <hi>Readeption</hi> of his <hi>uſurped Power</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> divers and many Matters were <hi>treated, communed, wrought to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and diſheriſon</hi> of our Sovereign Lord the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Blood Royal,</hi> by the Labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Exhortation of <hi>Perſons not fearing God, nor willing to be under the Rule of any earthly Prince,</hi> but incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of ſenſual Appetite to have the whole <hi>Governance</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of this <hi>Realm</hi> under their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Which <hi>Communications, Treaties</hi> and <hi>Workings</hi> do remain in Writing, and ſome exemplified; whereby many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences may enſue to our ſaid So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord the King, and his Blood Royal, (which God defend,) and all Noblemen at this time attending about the King, and all his other Liege People and Subjects, unleſs due Remedy be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in this behalf. Our ſaid Sovereign Lord the King, by the Aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and at the Requeſt of the Commons in the ſaid Parliament aſſembled, and by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſame, For the <hi>Surety</hi> of his <hi>noble Perſon,</hi> his <hi>noble Iſſue,</hi> and the <hi>inheritable Succeſſion</hi> of the ſame; and for the Surety of all the Lords, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and other his Servants and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, hath ordained and ſtabliſhed, that the ſaid <hi>pretenſed Parliament</hi> with all the Continuances and Circumſtances de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the ſame, be void, and of none effect; and that all <hi>Acts, Statutes, Ordinances, Treats, Communications, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions</hi> and Worki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gs in the ſame <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed Parliament treated, communed,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, wrought, had, or by Authority of the <hi>ſame Parliament</hi> enacted and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; and all Exemplifications made upon the ſame, or any part of them, and every of them, ſhall be reverſed, cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, void, undone, revoked, repealed, and of no fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce, nor effect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> VI. was a King <hi>de facto,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Author's Deſcription, as well before, at, and after this Parliament, in the Ninth of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. and Forty ninth of <hi>Henry</hi> VI. and is ſaid to be in this Statute; yet in all theſe Times he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59535:22"/> is declared an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> at this time a <hi>Rebel,</hi> and his Reign a <hi>pretenſed Reign;</hi> and this Parliament is alſo declared a <hi>pretenſed Parliament.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Statutes at large, <hi>1.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. <hi>VII.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Richard</hi> III. was acknowledged to be a King, by a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of his own calling, and was, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Author's deſcription, a King <hi>de facto;</hi> yet in the Firſt of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> VII. he is declared an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> of the Realm, and not ſo much as allowed the name of King, or <hi>pretenſed</hi> King, in that Statute.</p>
                  <p>After the King <hi>de facto,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> Enquiry is to be made what Right and Title a King <hi>de jure</hi> may pretend to the Crown, accordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g to the Conſtitution, Law, and Statutes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdom; and it appears by the following plain Proofs, that it is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y by <hi>Deſcent,</hi> and not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. This is an hereditary, ſucceſſive Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>archy; and immediately upon the Death o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ceſſion of th Predeceſſor, the Crown is veſted in the lawful Succeſſor by Inheritance and Proximity of Blood. Which appears,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By the Record before cited of the Comprom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe and Agreement between <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chard</hi> Duke of <hi>Yo k</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> VI. in the Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inth Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar of his R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ign, wherein he makes his Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m only by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcent. He exhibited only a bare Title by Deſcent, and Proximity of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> od, which could not be denied; and upon ſuch ſhewing of his Right, the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rds concluded, it could not be defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> IV. <hi>n.</hi> 10. This was p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> t of the Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tion and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſed into an Act. <hi>n.</hi> 15.</note> notwithſtanding what King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Council could ſay again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cord of the Firſt of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Commyns being in this preſent Parlement, having ſufficient and evident kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wlege of the ſeid <hi>unright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w ſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> and <hi>Intruſion, by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>id</hi> Henry <hi>late Erle of</hi> Derby, upon the ſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rone of <hi>Englond;</hi> knowing alſo certai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, <hi>without doubte or ambiguite,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Right and Title of our ſeid Soverayne Lord therunto true, and that by <hi>God's Law Manne's Law, and Law of Nature, he an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> none other is and owe to be their true, rightwiſe, and natural Liege and Soveraign Lord;</hi> and that he was <hi>in Right from the deth</hi> of the ſeid noble and famous P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce his Fader, <hi>very juſt King</hi> of the ſeid Reaume of <hi>England.</hi> And yet his Father was never poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed of the Crown.</p>
                  <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> And that the Takeing of Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Entree into the Exerciſe of the Roiall Eſtate, Dignite, Reign, and Governaunce of the ſeid Reaume of <hi>Englond,</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>Irelond,</hi> of our ſeid Soverayne Liege Lord King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV. the ſeid 4th Day of <hi>March;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">That Day he took Poſſeſſion of the Crown and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>Ibid. n.</hi> 11.</note> and the Amocion of the ſeid <hi>Henry,</hi> late called King <hi>Henry</hi> VI. from the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, Occupa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, Uſurpation, Intruſion, Reigne, and G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vernaunce of the ſeid Reaume and Lordſhip doon by our ſeid Soverayne, and L ege Lord King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV. the ſeid 4th Day of <hi>March,</hi> was and is rightwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, lawfull, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes and Cu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umes of the ſeid Reaume, and ſoe owe to be taken, holden, reputed, and accep ed. And over that, that our ſeid Sov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rayne, and Liege Lord King <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ward</hi> IV. the ſeid 4 h Day of <hi>March,</hi> was lawfully ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed and poſſeſſed of the ſeid Corone of <hi>Englond</hi> in his ſeid Right and Title; and from thencefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve to hym and his Heires, K ngs of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>glond,</hi> all ſuch Manners, Caſtells, Lordſhips, Honoures, Londs, Tenements, Rentes, Services, Fees, Fee-farm Rentes, Knights F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, Avouſons, Gyftes of Offices, to yere at his pleaſure, Feires, Markets, Iſſ es, Fynes and Amerciamentes, Libertees, Franchiſes, Prerogatifs, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chetes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes, Reverſions, Remey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ders, and all other Hereditamentes with her Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenaunces, whatſoever they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, in <hi>Englond, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Irelond,</hi> and in <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys,</hi> and the Marches therof, as the ſeid King <hi>Richard</hi> had in the Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> the Apoſtle, (about three Weeks before he was depoſed) the Twenty third Yere of his Reigne, in the Right and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tle of the Corone of <hi>Englond,</hi> and Lordſhip of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elond;</hi> and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er his Deceſſe, have deſcended to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59535:22"/> 
                     <hi>Edmund Mortymer Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche,</hi> Sonne of the ſeid <hi>Roger Mortymer Erle</hi> of <hi>Marche,</hi> as to the <hi>next Heire</hi> of <hi>Blode</hi> of the ſame King <hi>Richard,</hi> after his deth, yf the ſeid Uſurpation had not been committed; or after the ſeid <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> to his <hi>next Heire</hi> of <hi>Blode,</hi> by the <hi>Lawe</hi> and <hi>Cuſtume</hi> of the ſeid Reaume of <hi>Englond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The general Opinion of the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion in theſe Times, that the Right and Title to the Crown was by Inheritance only, and Proximity of Blood, cauſed <hi>Henry</hi> IV. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o claim it,<note place="margin">Rot. Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> Hen. <hi>IV.</hi> n. <hi>53.</hi> Rot. Parl. <hi>1</hi> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c. <hi>III. in</hi> Exact Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fol. <hi>712 713, 714.</hi>
                     </note> als <hi>deſcendit</hi> be <hi>ryght Lyne</hi> of the <hi>Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de,</hi> comeynge fro the gude Lord <hi>Henry</hi> Therde.</p>
                  <p>And for the ſame Reaſon, <hi>Richard</hi> III. was by the three Eſtates, that is to ſay, the Lords Spi itual and Temporal, and Commons, in Parliament aſſembled, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be <hi>undoubted Heir</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> Father to <hi>Edward</hi> IV. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Inheriter</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Dignity Royal,</hi> and, as <hi>in Right,</hi> King o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>England</hi> by way of <hi>Inheritance.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſſel</hi>'s C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. <hi>fol.</hi> 231.</note> All this was inſinuated by himſelf, in his Anſwer to <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s Speech, when he took upon him Kingſhip. Likewiſe <hi>Henry</hi> VII. upon the ſame Account, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers his Title by Conqueſt and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion before that by Act of Parliament, which Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> VIII.<note place="margin">In <hi>Cotton</hi>'s Library, <hi>Cleopatra, E.</hi> 3.</note> in his Bull of Confirmation of his Title, ſays, belonged to him, <hi>non modo jure belli, ac notorio &amp; indubitato proximo ſucceſſionis titulo, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum etiam omnium Praelatorum, Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Magnatum, Nobilium, totiuſque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem regni plebis Electione, &amp; noch &amp; decreto ſtatuto, &amp; ordinatione ipſius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae regni trium Statuum in ipſorum Conventu Parlamento nuncupato:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. <hi>f.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note> Not only by Right of War, (being ſaluted King by the Army in <hi>Boſworth</hi>-Field, and had there King <hi>Richard</hi>'s ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Crown put on by Sir <hi>William Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi>) and the notorious and indubitable next Title of Succeſſion; but alſo by the Election of all the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and <hi>Great Men</hi> of the who e Commonalty of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and by a known and decreed Statute and Ordinance of the three Eſtates of the ſame Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in their Meeting called a Parliament. But that he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt ſafe in the Pope's Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is clear, for that in the Thirteenth Year of his Reign he procured the Bull to be renewed, and the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment confirmed, by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VI.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cotton,</hi> Lib. ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> under pain of Excommunication and Curſe to ſuch as ſhould, upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever, diſturb the Peace of the Nation, and create Troubles againſt the Title of <hi>Henry</hi> VII.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. in all his extravagant Acts concerning his Queens, and the Succeſſion, founded them in pretended legal Proximity of Blood, according to the due courſe of Inheritance; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended want of which was the Ground and Suggeſtion ſtill for paſſing thoſe Acts. See 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. 28. <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. And 35. <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Statut. <hi>1.</hi> Mar. Seſſ. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> Where it hath pleaſed Almighty God, the 6th Day of <hi>July</hi> laſt paſt, to call out of this tranſitory Life, unto his Mercy, our late Sovereign Lord King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. by, and immediately after whoſe deceaſe, <hi>the Imperial Crown of this Realm, with all Dignities, Dominion, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nours, Pre-eminencies, Prerogatives, Stiles, Authorities, and Juriſdictions, to the ſame united, annexed, or belonging, did not only deſcend, remain and come unto our moſt dread Sovereign Lady the Queen's Majeſty,</hi> but alſo <hi>the ſame was then immediately, and lawfully inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſted, deemed and adj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dged</hi> in Her <hi>Highneſs's</hi> moſt Royal <hi>Perſon,</hi> by the due <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Inheritance,</hi> and by the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> of this R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alm.</p>
                  <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>1.</hi> Jac. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> The Act of <hi>Recognition</hi> in the Firſt of King <hi>James,</hi> doth not take notice of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. his Title, but of his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Margaret</hi>'s, as deſcended from <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> her Mother, Daughter and Heir to <hi>Edward</hi> IV. and declare, that he was <hi>lineally, rightfully</hi> and <hi>lawfully</hi> deſcended or the Body of the moſt excellent Lady
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59535:23"/> 
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> eldeſt Daughter of the moſt renowned King <hi>Henry</hi> VII. and the high and <hi>noble</hi> Princeſs Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, eldeſt Daug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> IV. In conſideration whereof, the Parliament doth acknowledge King <hi>James</hi> their <hi>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y rightful Liege Lord and Sovereign;</hi> and further ſay, as being <hi>bound thereunto both by the Laws of God and Man,</hi> they do recognize and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that <hi>immediately upon the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſolution and Deceaſe of</hi> Elizabeth <hi>late Queen of</hi> England, <hi>the Imperial Crown of the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Dominions and Rights belong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng to the ſame, did b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>erent Birth-right, and lawful and undoubted Succeſſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nd and come to His moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as being linea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly, juſtly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lawfully next and ſole Heir of the Blood Royal of this Realm;</hi> as it is aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>In the Firſt of the ſame King, there was a Conſpiracy formed againſt him, by Perſons of divers Perſuaſions:<note place="margin">Term. Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> Jac. <hi>kept at</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> 
                     <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Clerk,</hi> two Prieſts, pleaded it could not be Treaſon, <hi>becauſe he was not crowned.</hi> All the <hi>Judges</hi> reſolved, <hi>That King</hi> James <hi>being right Heir to the Crown by Deſcent, was immediately upon the death of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>actually p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſed of the Crown, and lawful K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng of</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gland, <hi>before any Proclamation, or Coronation of him, which were but Ceremonies.</hi> For their Treaſon they were condemned, and executed at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> the 29th of <hi>November.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are impregnable Proofs from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Conſtitution, Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of this Nation, what the Right and Title to the Crown is, and to whom the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion is due.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
